<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="3" category="info" consensus="true" docName="draft-iab-rfc7500-bis-00" indexInclude="true" ipr="trust200902" number="8720" obsoletes="7500" prepTime="2020-02-26T17:10:42" scripts="Common,Latin" sortRefs="true" submissionType="IAB" symRefs="true" tocDepth="3" tocInclude="true" xml:lang="en">
  <link href="https://dx.doi.org/10.17487/rfc8720" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="urn:issn:2070-1721" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-iab-rfc7500-bis-00" rel="prev"/>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Principles for Operation of IANA Registries">Principles for Operation of Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA) Registries</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8720" stream="IAB"/>
    <author fullname="Russ Housley" initials="R." role="editor" surname="Housley">
      <organization showOnFrontPage="false" abbrev="Vigil Security">Vigil Security, LLC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>918 Spring Knoll Drive</street>
          <city>Herndon</city>
          <region>VA</region>
          <code>20170</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>housley@vigilsec.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Olaf Kolkman" initials="O." role="editor" surname="Kolkman">
      <organization showOnFrontPage="false">Internet Society</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Science Park 400</street>
          <city>Amsterdam</city>
          <code>1098 XH</code>
          <country>NL</country>
        </postal>
        <email>kolkman@isoc.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="02" year="2020"/>
    <keyword>IASA</keyword>
    <abstract pn="section-abstract">
      <t pn="section-abstract-1">
   This document provides principles for the operation of Internet
   Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA) registries.</t>
    </abstract>
    <boilerplate>
      <section anchor="status-of-memo" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-boilerplate.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-status-of-this-memo">Status of This Memo</name>
        <t pn="section-boilerplate.1-1">
            This document is not an Internet Standards Track specification; it is
            published for informational purposes.  
        </t>
        <t pn="section-boilerplate.1-2">
            This document is a product of the Internet Architecture Board
            (IAB) and represents information that the IAB has deemed valuable
            to provide for permanent record.  It represents the consensus of the Internet
            Architecture Board (IAB).  Documents approved for publication
            by the IAB are not candidates for any level of Internet Standard; see
            Section 2 of RFC 7841.
        </t>
        <t pn="section-boilerplate.1-3">
            Information about the current status of this document, any
            errata, and how to provide feedback on it may be obtained at
            <eref target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8720" brackets="none"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="copyright" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-boilerplate.2">
        <name slugifiedName="name-copyright-notice">Copyright Notice</name>
        <t pn="section-boilerplate.2-1">
            Copyright (c) 2020 IETF Trust and the persons identified as the
            document authors. All rights reserved.
        </t>
        <t pn="section-boilerplate.2-2">
            This document is subject to BCP 78 and the IETF Trust's Legal
            Provisions Relating to IETF Documents
            (<eref target="https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info" brackets="none"/>) in effect on the date of
            publication of this document. Please review these documents
            carefully, as they describe your rights and restrictions with
            respect to this document.
        </t>
      </section>
    </boilerplate>
    <toc>
      <section anchor="toc" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-toc.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-table-of-contents">Table of Contents</name>
        <ul bare="true" empty="true" indent="2" spacing="compact" pn="section-toc.1-1">
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.1">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.1.1"><xref derivedContent="1" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-1"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-introduction">Introduction</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.1"><xref derivedContent="2" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-principles-for-the-operatio">Principles for the Operation of IANA Registries</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.3">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.3.1"><xref derivedContent="3" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-3"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-discussion">Discussion</xref></t>
            <ul bare="true" empty="true" indent="2" spacing="compact" pn="section-toc.1-1.3.2">
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.3.2.1">
                <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.3.2.1.1"><xref derivedContent="3.1" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-3.1"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-ensuring-uniqueness-stabili">Ensuring Uniqueness, Stability, and Predictability</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.3.2.2">
                <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.3.2.2.1"><xref derivedContent="3.2" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-3.2"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-public">Public</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.3.2.3">
                <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.3.2.3.1"><xref derivedContent="3.3" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-3.3"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-open-and-transparent">Open and Transparent</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.3.2.4">
                <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.3.2.4.1"><xref derivedContent="3.4" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-3.4"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-accountable">Accountable</xref></t>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.4">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.4.1"><xref derivedContent="4" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-4"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-security-considerations">Security Considerations</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.5">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.5.1"><xref derivedContent="5" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-5"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-changes-since-rfc-7500">Changes since RFC 7500</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.6">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.6.1"><xref derivedContent="6" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-6"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-informative-references">Informative References</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.7">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.7.1"><xref derivedContent="" format="none" sectionFormat="of" target="section-appendix.a"/><xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-iab-members-at-the-time-of-">IAB Members at the Time of Approval</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.8">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.8.1"><xref derivedContent="" format="none" sectionFormat="of" target="section-appendix.b"/><xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.9">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.9.1"><xref derivedContent="" format="none" sectionFormat="of" target="section-appendix.c"/><xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-authors-addresses">Authors' Addresses</xref></t>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </toc>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="sect-1" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-1">
      <name slugifiedName="name-introduction">Introduction</name>
      <t pn="section-1-1">
   The Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) and its predecessors have
   traditionally separated the publication of protocol specifications in
   immutable Request for Comments (RFCs) and the registries containing
   protocol parameters.  Traditionally, the registries are maintained by
   a set of functions known collectively as the Internet Assigned
   Numbers Authority (IANA).  Dating back to the earliest days of the
   Internet, specification publication and the registry operations were
   tightly coupled: Jon Postel of the Information Sciences Institute
   (ISI) of the University of Southern California (USC) was responsible
   for both RFC publication and IANA registry operation.  This tight
   coupling had advantages, but it was never a requirement.  Indeed,
   today, the RFC Editor and IANA registry operation are provided by
   different entities.</t>
      <t pn="section-1-2">
   Internet registries are critical to the operation of the Internet
   because they provide a definitive record of the value and meaning of
   identifiers that protocols use when communicating with each other.
   Almost every Internet protocol makes use of registries in some form.
   At the time of writing, the IANA maintains more than two thousand
   protocol parameter registries.</t>
      <t pn="section-1-3">
   Internet registries hold protocol identifiers consisting of constants
   and other well-known values used by Internet protocols.  These values
   can be numbers, strings, addresses, and so on.  They are uniquely
   assigned for one particular purpose or use.  Identifiers can be
   maintained in a central list (such as a list of cryptographic
   algorithms), or they can be hierarchically allocated and assigned by
   separate entities at different points in the hierarchy (such as IP
   addresses and domain names).  To maximize trust and usefulness of the
   IANA registries, the principles in this document should be taken into
   consideration for centralized registries as well as hierarchically
   delegated registries.  In hierarchically delegated registries,
   entries nearest to top level have broad scope, but lower-level
   entries have narrow scope.  The Internet Architecture Board (IAB)
   will encourage support for these principles in all delegations of
   Internet identifiers.</t>
      <t pn="section-1-4">
   The registry system is built on trust and mutual cooperation.  The
   use of the registries is voluntary and is not enforced by mandates or
   certification policies.  While the use of registries is voluntary, it
   is noted that the success of the Internet creates enormous pressure
   to use Internet protocols and the identifier registries associated
   with them.</t>
      <t pn="section-1-5">
   This document provides principles for the operation of IANA
   registries, ensuring that protocol identifiers have consistent
   meanings and interpretations across all implementations and
   deployments, thus providing the necessary trust in the IANA
   registries.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sect-2" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-2">
      <name slugifiedName="name-principles-for-the-operatio">Principles for the Operation of IANA Registries</name>
      <t pn="section-2-1">
   The following key principles underscore the successful functioning of
   the IANA registries, and they provide a foundation for trust in those
   registries:</t>
      <dl newline="true" spacing="normal" pn="section-2-2">
        <dt pn="section-2-2.1">Ensure Uniqueness:</dt>
        <dd pn="section-2-2.2"> The same protocol identifier must not be
   used for more than one purpose.</dd>
        <dt pn="section-2-2.3">Stable:</dt>
        <dd pn="section-2-2.4">Protocol identifier assignment must be lasting.</dd>
        <dt pn="section-2-2.5">Predictable:</dt>
        <dd pn="section-2-2.6">The process for making assignments must not
	include unexpected steps. </dd>
        <dt pn="section-2-2.7">Public:</dt>
        <dd pn="section-2-2.8"> The protocol identifiers must be made available
	in well-known locations in a manner that makes them freely available
	to everyone. </dd>
        <dt pn="section-2-2.9">Open:</dt>
        <dd pn="section-2-2.10">The process that sets the policy for protocol
	identifier assignment and registration must be open to all interested
        parties.</dd>
        <dt pn="section-2-2.11">Transparent:</dt>
        <dd pn="section-2-2.12">The protocol registries and their
	associated policies should be developed in a transparent manner.</dd>
        <dt pn="section-2-2.13">Accountable:</dt>
        <dd pn="section-2-2.14">Registry policy development and registry
	operations need to be accountable to the affected community.</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sect-3" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-3">
      <name slugifiedName="name-discussion">Discussion</name>
      <t pn="section-3-1">
   The principles discussed in <xref target="sect-2" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="Section 2"/> provide trust and confidence in
   the IANA registries.  This section expands on these principles.</t>
      <section anchor="sect-3.1" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-3.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-ensuring-uniqueness-stabili">Ensuring Uniqueness, Stability, and Predictability</name>
        <t pn="section-3.1-1">
   Protocol identifier assignment and registration must be unique,
   stable, and predictable.  Developers, vendors, customers, and users
   depend on the registries for unique protocol identifiers that are
   assigned in a stable and predictable manner.</t>
        <t pn="section-3.1-2">
   A protocol identifier may only be reassigned for a different purpose
   after due consideration of the impact of such a reassignment and, if
   possible, with the consent of the original assignee.</t>
        <t pn="section-3.1-3">
   Recognizing that some assignments involve judgment, such as those
   involving a designated expert <xref target="RFC8126" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8126"/>, a predictable process does
   not require completion in a predetermined number of days.  Rather, it
   means that no unexpected steps are introduced in the process of
   making an assignment.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-3.2" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-3.2">
        <name slugifiedName="name-public">Public</name>
        <t pn="section-3.2-1">
   Once assigned, the protocol identifiers must be made available in a
   manner that makes them freely available to everyone without
   restrictions.  The use of a consistent publication location builds
   confidence in the registry.  This does not mean that the publication
   location can never change, but it does mean that it must change
   infrequently and only after adequate prior notice.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-3.3" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-3.3">
        <name slugifiedName="name-open-and-transparent">Open and Transparent</name>
        <t pn="section-3.3-1">
   The process that sets the policy for protocol identifier assignment
   and registration must be open to all interested parties and must operate
   in a transparent manner.</t>
        <t pn="section-3.3-2">
   When a registry is established, a policy is set for the addition of
   new entries and the updating of existing entries.  While making
   additions and modifications, the registry operator may expose
   instances where policies lack clarity.  When this occurs, the
   registry operator should provide helpful feedback to allow those
   policies to be improved.  In addition, the registry operator not
   being involved in establishing registry policy avoids the risks
   associated with (perceptions of) favoritism and unfairness.</t>
        <t pn="section-3.3-3">
   Recognizing that some assignments involve judgment, such as those
   involving a designated expert <xref target="RFC8126" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8126"/>, the recommendations by
   designated experts must be visible to the public to the maximum
   extent possible and subject to challenge or appeal.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-3.4" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-3.4">
        <name slugifiedName="name-accountable">Accountable</name>
        <t pn="section-3.4-1">
   The process that sets the policy for IANA registries and the
   operation of the registries must be accountable to the parties that
   rely on the protocol identifiers.  Oversight is needed to ensure
   these are properly serving the affected community.</t>
        <t pn="section-3.4-2">
   In practice, accountability mechanisms for the registry operator may
   be defined by a contract, memoranda of understanding, or service level
   agreements (SLAs).  An oversight body uses these mechanisms to ensure
   that the registry operator is meeting the needs of the affected
   community.  The oversight body is held accountable to the affected
   community by vastly different mechanisms -- for instance, recall and
   appeal processes.</t>
        <t pn="section-3.4-3">
   For protocol parameters <xref target="RFC6220" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC6220"/>, the general oversight of the IANA
   function is performed by the IAB as a chartered responsibility from
   <xref target="RFC2850" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC2850"/>.  In addition, the IETF Administration Limited Liability
   Company (IETF LLC), as part of the IETF Administrative Support
   Activity (IASA), is responsible for IETF administrative and financial
   matters <xref target="RFC8711" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8711"/>. In that role, the IETF LLC
   maintains an SLA with the current registry operator, the Internet
   Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers (ICANN), thereby
   specifying the operational requirements with respect to the
   coordination, maintenance, and publication of the protocol parameter
   registries.  Both the IAB and the Board of the IETF LLC are
   accountable to the larger Internet community and are being held
   accountable through the IETF NomCom process <xref target="RFC8713" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8713"/>.</t>
        <t pn="section-3.4-4">
   For the Internet Number Registries <xref target="RFC7249" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC7249"/>, oversight is performed
   by the Regional Internet Registries (RIRs) as described RFC 7020
   <xref target="RFC7020" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC7020"/>.  The RIRs are member-based organizations, and they are
   accountable to the affected community by elected governance boards.
   Furthermore, per agreement between the RIRs and ICANN, the policy
   development for the global IANA number registries is coordinated by a
   community-elected number council and subject to process review before
   ratification by the ICANN Board of Trustees <xref target="ASOMOU" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="ASOMOU"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sect-4" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-4">
      <name slugifiedName="name-security-considerations">Security Considerations</name>
      <t pn="section-4-1">
   Internet registries are critical to elements of Internet security.
   The principles described in this document are necessary for the
   Internet community to place trust in the IANA registries.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sect-5" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-5">
      <name slugifiedName="name-changes-since-rfc-7500">Changes since RFC 7500</name>
      <t pn="section-5-1">
   <xref target="sect-3.4" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="Section 3.4"/> has been updated to align with the restructuring of the
   IETF Administrative Support Activity (IASA).  Under the new
   structure, the IETF LLC maintains an SLA with the protocol parameter
   registry operator.  Under the old structure, the SLA was maintained
   by the IETF Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC).</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references pn="section-6">
      <name slugifiedName="name-informative-references">Informative References</name>
      <reference anchor="ASOMOU" target="https://archive.icann.org/en/aso/aso-mou-29oct04.htm" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="ASOMOU">
        <front>
          <title>Address Supporting Organization (ASO) MoU</title>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">ICANN</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2004"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC2850" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2850" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC2850">
        <front>
          <title>Charter of the Internet Architecture Board (IAB)</title>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Internet Architecture Board</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="B." surname="Carpenter" fullname="B. Carpenter" role="editor">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <date year="2000" month="May"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>This memo documents the composition, selection, roles, and organization of the Internet Architecture Board.  It replaces RFC 1601.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="39"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2850"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC2850"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC6220" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6220" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC6220">
        <front>
          <title>Defining the Role and Function of IETF Protocol Parameter Registry Operators</title>
          <author initials="D." surname="McPherson" fullname="D. McPherson" role="editor">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="O." surname="Kolkman" fullname="O. Kolkman" role="editor">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Klensin" fullname="J. Klensin" role="editor">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="G." surname="Huston" fullname="G. Huston" role="editor">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Internet Architecture Board</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2011" month="April"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>Many Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) protocols make use of commonly defined values that are passed in messages or packets.  To ensure consistent interpretation of these values between independent implementations, there is a need to ensure that the values and associated semantic intent are uniquely defined.  The IETF uses registry functions to record assigned protocol parameter values and their associated semantic intentions.  For each IETF protocol parameter, it is current practice for the IETF to delegate the role of Protocol Parameter Registry Operator to a nominated entity.  This document provides a description of, and the requirements for, these delegated functions.  This document is not an  Internet Standards Track specification; it is published for informational  purposes.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6220"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC6220"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC7020" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7020" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC7020">
        <front>
          <title>The Internet Numbers Registry System</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Housley" fullname="R. Housley">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Curran" fullname="J. Curran">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="G." surname="Huston" fullname="G. Huston">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="D." surname="Conrad" fullname="D. Conrad">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <date year="2013" month="August"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>This document provides information about the current Internet Numbers Registry System used in the distribution of globally unique Internet Protocol (IP) address space and autonomous system (AS) numbers.</t>
            <t>This document also provides information about the processes for further evolution of the Internet Numbers Registry System.</t>
            <t>This document replaces RFC 2050.</t>
            <t>This document does not propose any changes to the current Internet Numbers Registry System.  Rather, it documents the Internet Numbers Registry System as it works today.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7020"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7020"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC7249" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7249" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC7249">
        <front>
          <title>Internet Numbers Registries</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Housley" fullname="R. Housley">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <date year="2014" month="May"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>RFC 7020 provides information about the Internet Numbers Registry System and how it is used in the distribution of autonomous system (AS) numbers and globally unique unicast Internet Protocol (IP) address space.</t>
            <t>This companion document identifies the IANA registries that are part of the Internet Numbers Registry System at this time.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7249"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7249"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC8126" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8126" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8126">
        <front>
          <title>Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Cotton" fullname="M. Cotton">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="B." surname="Leiba" fullname="B. Leiba">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="T." surname="Narten" fullname="T. Narten">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <date year="2017" month="June"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>Many protocols make use of points of extensibility that use constants to identify various protocol parameters.  To ensure that the values in these fields do not have conflicting uses and to promote interoperability, their allocations are often coordinated by a central record keeper.  For IETF protocols, that role is filled by the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA).</t>
            <t>To make assignments in a given registry prudently, guidance describing the conditions under which new values should be assigned, as well as when and how modifications to existing values can be made, is needed.  This document defines a framework for the documentation of these guidelines by specification authors, in order to assure that the provided guidance for the IANA Considerations is clear and addresses the various issues that are likely in the operation of a registry.</t>
            <t>This is the third edition of this document; it obsoletes RFC 5226.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="26"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8126"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8126"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC8711" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8711" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8711">
        <front>
          <title>Structure of the IETF Administrative Support Activity, Version 2.0</title>
          <author initials="B" surname="Haberman" fullname="Brian Haberman">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J" surname="Hall" fullname="Joseph Hall">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J" surname="Livingood" fullname="Jason Livingood">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <date month="February" year="2020"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="101"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8711"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8711"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC8713" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8713" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8713">
        <front>
          <title>IAB, IESG, and IETF LLC Selection, Confirmation, and Recall Process: Operation of the IETF Nominating and Recall Committees</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Kucherawy" role="editor">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="R." surname="Hinden" role="editor">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Livingood" role="editor">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <date month="February" year="2020"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="10"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8713"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8713"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <section anchor="sect-iab" numbered="false" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-appendix.a">
      <name slugifiedName="name-iab-members-at-the-time-of-">IAB Members at the Time of Approval</name>
      <ul spacing="compact" empty="true" bare="false" pn="section-appendix.a-1">
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-1.1">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-1.1.1"><contact fullname="Jari Arkko"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-1.2">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-1.2.1"><contact fullname="Alissa Cooper"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-1.3">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-1.3.1"><contact fullname="Stephen Farrell"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-1.4">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-1.4.1"><contact fullname="Wes Hardaker"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-1.5">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-1.5.1"><contact fullname="Ted Hardie"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-1.6">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-1.6.1"><contact fullname="Christian Huitema"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-1.7">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-1.7.1"><contact fullname="Zhenbin Li"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-1.8">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-1.8.1"><contact fullname="Erik Nordmark"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-1.9">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-1.9.1"><contact fullname="Mark Nottingham"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-1.10">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-1.10.1"><contact fullname="Melinda Shore"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-1.11">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-1.11.1"><contact fullname="Jeff Tantsura"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-1.12">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-1.12.1"><contact fullname="Martin Thomson"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-1.13">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-1.13.1"><contact fullname="Brian Trammell"/></t>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section numbered="false" anchor="acknowledgements" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-appendix.b">
      <name slugifiedName="name-acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</name>
      <t pn="section-appendix.b-1">
   This text has been developed within the IAB IANA Evolution Program.
   The ideas and many text fragments and corrections came from or were
   inspired by comments from:
<contact fullname="Bernard Aboba"/>,
<contact fullname="Jaap Akkerhuis"/>,
<contact fullname="Jari Arkko"/>,
<contact fullname="Marcelo Bagnulo"/>,
<contact fullname="Mark Blanchet"/>,
<contact fullname="Brian Carpenter"/>,
<contact fullname="David Conrad"/>,
<contact fullname="Alissa Cooper"/>,
<contact fullname="Steve Crocker"/>,
<contact fullname="John Curran"/>,
<contact fullname="Leslie Daigle"/>,
<contact fullname="Elise Gerich"/>,
<contact fullname="John Klensin"/>,
<contact fullname="Bertrand de La Chapelle"/>,
<contact fullname="Eliot Lear"/>,
<contact fullname="Danny McPherson"/>,
<contact fullname="George Michaelson"/>,
<contact fullname="Thomas Narten"/>,
<contact fullname="Andrei Robachevsky"/>,
<contact fullname="Andrew Sullivan"/>,
<contact fullname="Dave Thaler"/>,
<contact fullname="Brian Trammell"/>,
and <contact fullname="Greg Wood"/>. 

   Further inspiration and input
   was drawn from various meetings with the leadership of the Internet
   community, i.e., from the RIRs, ISOC, W3C, IETF, and IAB.
      </t>
      <t pn="section-appendix.b-2">
   Please do not assume those acknowledged endorse the resulting text.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="authors-addresses" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-appendix.c">
      <name slugifiedName="name-authors-addresses">Authors' Addresses</name>
      <author fullname="Russ Housley" initials="R." role="editor" surname="Housley">
        <organization showOnFrontPage="false" abbrev="Vigil Security">Vigil Security, LLC</organization>
        <address>
          <postal>
            <street>918 Spring Knoll Drive</street>
            <city>Herndon</city>
            <region>VA</region>
            <code>20170</code>
            <country>United States of America</country>
          </postal>
          <email>housley@vigilsec.com</email>
        </address>
      </author>
      <author fullname="Olaf Kolkman" initials="O." role="editor" surname="Kolkman">
        <organization showOnFrontPage="false">Internet Society</organization>
        <address>
          <postal>
            <street>Science Park 400</street>
            <city>Amsterdam</city>
            <code>1098 XH</code>
            <country>NL</country>
          </postal>
          <email>kolkman@isoc.org</email>
        </address>
      </author>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
