<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="3" category="std" consensus="true" docName="draft-ietf-rtcweb-alpn-04" indexInclude="true" ipr="trust200902" number="8833" prepTime="2021-01-16T21:51:18" scripts="Common,Latin" sortRefs="true" submissionType="IETF" symRefs="true" tocDepth="4" tocInclude="true" xml:lang="en">
  <link href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-rtcweb-alpn-04" rel="prev"/>
  <link href="https://dx.doi.org/10.17487/rfc8833" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="urn:issn:2070-1721" rel="alternate"/>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ALPN for WebRTC">Application-Layer Protocol Negotiation (ALPN) for WebRTC</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8833" stream="IETF"/>
    <author initials="M." surname="Thomson" fullname="Martin Thomson">
      <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Mozilla</organization>
      <address>
        <postal/>
        <email>martin.thomson@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="01" year="2021"/>
    <keyword>ALPN</keyword>
    <keyword>Protocol</keyword>
    <keyword>Identifier</keyword>
    <abstract pn="section-abstract">
      <t indent="0" pn="section-abstract-1">
        This document specifies two Application-Layer Protocol Negotiation (ALPN) labels for use
        with Web Real-Time Communication (WebRTC).  The "webrtc" label identifies regular WebRTC:
        a DTLS session that is used to establish keys for the Secure Real-time Transport
        Protocol (SRTP) or to establish data channels using the Stream Control
	Transmission Protocol (SCTP) over DTLS.  The "c-webrtc" label
        describes the same protocol, but the peers also agree to maintain the confidentiality of the
        media by not sharing it with other applications.
      </t>
    </abstract>
    <boilerplate>
      <section anchor="status-of-memo" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-boilerplate.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-status-of-this-memo">Status of This Memo</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.1-1">
            This is an Internet Standards Track document.
        </t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.1-2">
            This document is a product of the Internet Engineering Task Force
            (IETF).  It represents the consensus of the IETF community.  It has
            received public review and has been approved for publication by
            the Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG).  Further
            information on Internet Standards is available in Section 2 of 
            RFC 7841.
        </t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.1-3">
            Information about the current status of this document, any
            errata, and how to provide feedback on it may be obtained at
            <eref target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8833" brackets="none"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="copyright" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-boilerplate.2">
        <name slugifiedName="name-copyright-notice">Copyright Notice</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.2-1">
            Copyright (c) 2021 IETF Trust and the persons identified as the
            document authors. All rights reserved.
        </t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.2-2">
            This document is subject to BCP 78 and the IETF Trust's Legal
            Provisions Relating to IETF Documents
            (<eref target="https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info" brackets="none"/>) in effect on the date of
            publication of this document. Please review these documents
            carefully, as they describe your rights and restrictions with
            respect to this document. Code Components extracted from this
            document must include Simplified BSD License text as described in
            Section 4.e of the Trust Legal Provisions and are provided without
            warranty as described in the Simplified BSD License.
        </t>
      </section>
    </boilerplate>
    <toc>
      <section anchor="toc" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-toc.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-table-of-contents">Table of Contents</name>
        <ul bare="true" empty="true" indent="2" spacing="compact" pn="section-toc.1-1">
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.1">
            <t indent="0" keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.1.1"><xref derivedContent="1" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-1"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-introduction">Introduction</xref></t>
            <ul bare="true" empty="true" indent="2" spacing="compact" pn="section-toc.1-1.1.2">
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.1.2.1">
                <t indent="0" keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.1.2.1.1"><xref derivedContent="1.1" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-1.1"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-conventions">Conventions</xref></t>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2">
            <t indent="0" keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.1"><xref derivedContent="2" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-alpn-labels-for-webrtc">ALPN Labels for WebRTC</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.3">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.3.1"><xref derivedContent="3" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-3"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-media-confidentiality">Media Confidentiality</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.4">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.4.1"><xref derivedContent="4" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-4"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-security-considerations">Security Considerations</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.5">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.5.1"><xref derivedContent="5" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-5"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-iana-considerations">IANA Considerations</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.6">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.6.1"><xref derivedContent="6" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-6"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-references">References</xref></t>
            <ul bare="true" empty="true" indent="2" spacing="compact" pn="section-toc.1-1.6.2">
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.6.2.1">
                <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.6.2.1.1"><xref derivedContent="6.1" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-6.1"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-normative-references">Normative References</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.6.2.2">
                <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.6.2.2.1"><xref derivedContent="6.2" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-6.2"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-informative-references">Informative References</xref></t>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.7">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.7.1"><xref derivedContent="" format="none" sectionFormat="of" target="section-appendix.a"/><xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-authors-address">Author's Address</xref></t>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </toc>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-1">
      <name slugifiedName="name-introduction">Introduction</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-1">
        <xref target="RFC8825" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8825">Web Real-Time Communication (WebRTC)</xref> uses
        <xref target="RFC6347" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC6347">Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS)</xref> to secure all
        peer-to-peer communications.
      </t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-2">
        Identifying WebRTC protocol usage with <xref target="RFC7301" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC7301">Application-Layer Protocol
        Negotiation (ALPN)</xref> enables an endpoint to positively identify WebRTC uses and
        distinguish them from other DTLS uses.
      </t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-3">
        Different WebRTC uses can be advertised and behavior can be constrained to what is
        appropriate to a given use.  In particular, this allows for the identification of sessions
        that require confidentiality protection from the application that manages the signaling for
        the session.
      </t>
      <section anchor="terminology" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-1.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-conventions">Conventions</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-1.1-1">
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-2">
      <name slugifiedName="name-alpn-labels-for-webrtc">ALPN Labels for WebRTC</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-2-1">
        The following identifiers are defined for use in ALPN:
      </t>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal" indent="3" pn="section-2-2">
        <dt pn="section-2-2.1">webrtc:</dt>
        <dd pn="section-2-2.2">
            The DTLS session is used to establish keys for the Secure Real-time Transport Protocol
            (SRTP) -- known as DTLS-SRTP -- as described in <xref target="RFC5764" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC5764"/>.  The DTLS record
            layer is used for <xref target="RFC8831" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8831">WebRTC data
            channels</xref>.
          </dd>
        <dt pn="section-2-2.3">c-webrtc:</dt>
        <dd pn="section-2-2.4">
            The DTLS session is used for confidential WebRTC, where peers agree to
            maintain the confidentiality of the media, as described in <xref target="confidentiality" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="Section 3"/>. The confidentiality protections ensure that media is
            protected from other applications, but the confidentiality protections do not extend to
            messages on data channels.
          </dd>
      </dl>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-2-3">
        Both identifiers describe the same basic protocol: a DTLS session that is used to provide
        keys for an SRTP session in combination with WebRTC data channels.  Either SRTP or data
        channels could be absent.  The data channels send the <xref target="RFC4960" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC4960">Stream Control
        Transmission Protocol (SCTP)</xref> over the DTLS record layer, which can be multiplexed
        with SRTP on the same UDP flow.  WebRTC requires the use of <xref target="RFC8445" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8445">Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE)</xref> to establish UDP
        flow, but this is not covered by the identifier.
      </t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-2-4">
        A more thorough definition of what WebRTC entails is included in <xref target="RFC8835" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8835"/>.
      </t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-2-5">
        There is no functional difference between the identifiers except that an endpoint
        negotiating <tt>c-webrtc</tt> makes a promise to preserve the
        confidentiality of the media it receives.
      </t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-2-6">
        A peer that is not aware of whether it needs to request confidentiality can use either
        identifier.  A peer in the client role <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> offer both identifiers if it is not aware of a
        need for confidentiality. A peer in the server role <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> select <tt>webrtc</tt> if it does not prefer either.
      </t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-2-7">
        An endpoint that requires media confidentiality might negotiate a session with a peer that
        does not support this specification.  An endpoint <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> abort a session if it requires
        confidentiality but does not successfully negotiate <tt>c-webrtc</tt>.  A
        peer that is willing to accept <tt>webrtc</tt> <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> assume that a peer
        that does not support this specification has negotiated <tt>webrtc</tt>
        unless signaling provides other information; however, a peer <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> assume that <tt>c-webrtc</tt> has been negotiated unless explicitly negotiated.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="confidentiality" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-3">
      <name slugifiedName="name-media-confidentiality">Media Confidentiality</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-1">
        Private communications in WebRTC depend on separating control (i.e., signaling) capabilities
        and access to media <xref target="RFC8827" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8827"/>.  In this way, an
        application can establish a session that is end-to-end confidential, where the ends in
        question are user agents (or browsers) and not the signaling application.  This allows an
        application to manage signaling for a session without having access to the media that is
        exchanged in the session.
      </t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-2">
        Without some form of indication that is securely bound to the session, a WebRTC endpoint is
        unable to properly distinguish between a session that requires this confidentiality
        protection and one that does not.  The ALPN identifier provides that signal.
      </t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-3">
        A browser is required to enforce this confidentiality protection using isolation controls
        similar to those used in content cross-origin protections
(see the "Origin" section of <xref target="HTML5" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="HTML5"/>).
  These protections ensure that media is protected from
        applications, which are not able to read or modify the contents of a protected flow
        of media.  Media that is produced from a session using the <tt>c-webrtc</tt> identifier <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only be displayed to users.
      </t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-4">
        The promise to apply confidentiality protections do not apply to data that is sent using
        data channels.  Confidential data depends on having both data sources and consumers that are
        exclusively browser or user based.  No mechanisms currently exist to take advantage of data
        confidentiality, though some use cases suggest that this could be useful, for example,
        confidential peer-to-peer file transfer.  Alternative labels might be
	provided in the future to support these use cases.
      </t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-5">
        This mechanism explicitly does not define a specific authentication method; a WebRTC
        endpoint that accepts a session with this ALPN identifier <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> respect confidentiality no
        matter what identity is attributed to a peer.
      </t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-6">
        RTP middleboxes and entities that forward media or data cannot promise to maintain
        confidentiality.  Any entity that forwards content, or records content for later access by
        entities other than the authenticated peer, <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> offer or accept a session with the
        <tt>c-webrtc</tt> identifier.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-4">
      <name slugifiedName="name-security-considerations">Security Considerations</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-1">
        Confidential communications depend on more than just an agreement from browsers.
      </t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-2">
        Information is not confidential if it is displayed to others than for whom it is
        intended.  <xref target="RFC8827" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8827">Peer authentication</xref> is
        necessary to ensure that data is only sent to the intended peer.
      </t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-3">
        This is not a digital rights management mechanism. A user is not prevented from using other
        mechanisms to record or forward media.  This means that (for example) screen-recording
        devices, tape recorders, portable cameras, or a cunning arrangement of mirrors could
        variously be used to record or redistribute media once delivered.  Similarly, if media is
        visible or audible (or otherwise accessible) to others in the vicinity, there are no
        technical measures that protect the confidentiality of that media.
      </t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-4">
        The only guarantee provided by this mechanism and the browser that implements it is that the
        media was delivered to the user that was authenticated.  Individual users will still need to
        make a judgment about how their peer intends to respect the confidentiality of any
        information provided.
      </t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-5">
        On a shared computing platform like a browser, other entities with access to that platform
        (i.e., web applications) might be able to access information that would compromise the
        confidentiality of communications.  Implementations <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> choose to limit concurrent access to
        input devices during confidential communications sessions.
      </t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-6">
        For instance, another application that is able to access a microphone might be able to
        sample confidential audio that is playing through speakers.  This is true even if acoustic
        echo cancellation, which attempts to prevent this from happening, is used.  Similarly, an
        application with access to a video camera might be able to use reflections to obtain all or
        part of a confidential video stream.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-5">
      <name slugifiedName="name-iana-considerations">IANA Considerations</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-5-1">
        The following two entries have been added to the "TLS Application-Layer
	Protocol Negotiation (ALPN) Protocol IDs" registry established by
	<xref target="RFC7301" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC7301"/>:
      </t>
      <dl newline="true" spacing="normal" indent="3" pn="section-5-2">
        <dt pn="section-5-2.1">webrtc:</dt>
        <dd pn="section-5-2.2">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-5-2.2.1">
            The <tt>webrtc</tt> label identifies mixed media and data
            communications using SRTP and data channels:
          </t>
          <dl newline="false" spacing="normal" indent="3" pn="section-5-2.2.2">
            <dt pn="section-5-2.2.2.1">Protocol:</dt>
            <dd pn="section-5-2.2.2.2">WebRTC Media and Data</dd>
            <dt pn="section-5-2.2.2.3">Identification Sequence:</dt>
            <dd pn="section-5-2.2.2.4">0x77 0x65 0x62 0x72 0x74 0x63 ("webrtc")</dd>
            <dt pn="section-5-2.2.2.5">Specification:</dt>
            <dd pn="section-5-2.2.2.6">RFC 8833 (this document)</dd>
          </dl>
        </dd>
        <dt pn="section-5-2.3">c-webrtc:</dt>
        <dd pn="section-5-2.4">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-5-2.4.1">
            The <tt>c-webrtc</tt> label identifies WebRTC
            with a promise to protect media confidentiality:
          </t>
          <dl newline="false" spacing="normal" indent="3" pn="section-5-2.4.2">
            <dt pn="section-5-2.4.2.1">Protocol:</dt>
            <dd pn="section-5-2.4.2.2">Confidential WebRTC Media and Data</dd>
            <dt pn="section-5-2.4.2.3">Identification Sequence:</dt>
            <dd pn="section-5-2.4.2.4">0x63 0x2d 0x77 0x65 0x62 0x72 0x74 0x63
              ("c-webrtc")</dd>
            <dt pn="section-5-2.4.2.5">Specification:</dt>
            <dd pn="section-5-2.4.2.6">RFC 8833 (this document)</dd>
          </dl>
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references pn="section-6">
      <name slugifiedName="name-references">References</name>
      <references pn="section-6.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-normative-references">Normative References</name>
        <reference anchor="RFC2119" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC2119">
          <front>
            <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
            <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="S. Bradner">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="1997" month="March"/>
            <abstract>
              <t indent="0">In many standards track documents several words are used to signify the requirements in the specification.  These words are often capitalized. This document defines these words as they should be interpreted in IETF documents.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC2119"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC5764" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5764" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC5764">
          <front>
            <title>Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) Extension to Establish Keys for the Secure Real-time Transport Protocol (SRTP)</title>
            <author initials="D." surname="McGrew" fullname="D. McGrew">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="E." surname="Rescorla" fullname="E. Rescorla">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2010" month="May"/>
            <abstract>
              <t indent="0">This document describes a Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) extension to establish keys for Secure RTP (SRTP) and Secure RTP Control Protocol (SRTCP) flows.  DTLS keying happens on the media path, independent of any out-of-band signalling channel present. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5764"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC5764"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC6347" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6347" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC6347">
          <front>
            <title>Datagram Transport Layer Security Version 1.2</title>
            <author initials="E." surname="Rescorla" fullname="E. Rescorla">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="N." surname="Modadugu" fullname="N. Modadugu">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2012" month="January"/>
            <abstract>
              <t indent="0">This document specifies version 1.2 of the Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) protocol.  The DTLS protocol provides communications privacy for datagram protocols.  The protocol allows client/server applications to communicate in a way that is designed to prevent eavesdropping, tampering, or message forgery.  The DTLS protocol is based on the Transport Layer Security (TLS) protocol and provides equivalent security guarantees.  Datagram semantics of the underlying transport are preserved by the DTLS protocol.  This document updates DTLS 1.0 to work with TLS version 1.2.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6347"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC6347"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC7301" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7301" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC7301">
          <front>
            <title>Transport Layer Security (TLS) Application-Layer Protocol Negotiation Extension</title>
            <author initials="S." surname="Friedl" fullname="S. Friedl">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="A." surname="Popov" fullname="A. Popov">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="A." surname="Langley" fullname="A. Langley">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="E." surname="Stephan" fullname="E. Stephan">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2014" month="July"/>
            <abstract>
              <t indent="0">This document describes a Transport Layer Security (TLS) extension for application-layer protocol negotiation within the TLS handshake. For instances in which multiple application protocols are supported on the same TCP or UDP port, this extension allows the application layer to negotiate which protocol will be used within the TLS connection.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7301"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7301"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC8174" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8174" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8174">
          <front>
            <title>Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC 2119 Key Words</title>
            <author initials="B." surname="Leiba" fullname="B. Leiba">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2017" month="May"/>
            <abstract>
              <t indent="0">RFC 2119 specifies common key words that may be used in protocol  specifications.  This document aims to reduce the ambiguity by clarifying that only UPPERCASE usage of the key words have the  defined special meanings.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8174"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8174"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC8827" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8827" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8827">
          <front>
            <title>WebRTC Security Architecture</title>
            <author initials="E." surname="Rescorla" fullname="Eric Rescorla">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date month="January" year="2021"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8827"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8827"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC8831" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8831" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8831">
          <front>
            <title>WebRTC Data Channels</title>
            <author initials="R" surname="Jesup" fullname="Randell Jesup">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="S" surname="Loreto" fullname="Salvatore Loreto">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="M" surname="Tüxen" fullname="Michael Tüxen">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date month="January" year="2021"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8831"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8831"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
      <references pn="section-6.2">
        <name slugifiedName="name-informative-references">Informative References</name>
        <reference anchor="HTML5" target="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/#origin" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="HTML5">
          <front>
            <title>HTML - Living Standard</title>
            <author>
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true">WHATWG</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="January" year="2021"/>
          </front>
          <refcontent>Section 7.5</refcontent>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC4960" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4960" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC4960">
          <front>
            <title>Stream Control Transmission Protocol</title>
            <author initials="R." surname="Stewart" fullname="R. Stewart" role="editor">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2007" month="September"/>
            <abstract>
              <t indent="0">This document obsoletes RFC 2960 and RFC 3309.  It describes the Stream Control Transmission Protocol (SCTP).  SCTP is designed to transport Public Switched Telephone Network (PSTN) signaling messages over IP networks, but is capable of broader applications.</t>
              <t indent="0">SCTP is a reliable transport protocol operating on top of a connectionless packet network such as IP.  It offers the following services to its users:</t>
              <t indent="0">--  acknowledged error-free non-duplicated transfer of user data,</t>
              <t indent="0">--  data fragmentation to conform to discovered path MTU size,</t>
              <t indent="0">--  sequenced delivery of user messages within multiple streams, with an option for order-of-arrival delivery of individual user messages,</t>
              <t indent="0">--  optional bundling of multiple user messages into a single SCTP packet, and</t>
              <t indent="0">--  network-level fault tolerance through supporting of multi-homing at either or both ends of an association.</t>
              <t indent="0"> The design of SCTP includes appropriate congestion avoidance behavior and resistance to flooding and masquerade attacks.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4960"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC4960"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC8445" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8445" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8445">
          <front>
            <title>Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE): A Protocol for Network Address Translator (NAT) Traversal</title>
            <author initials="A." surname="Keranen" fullname="A. Keranen">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="C." surname="Holmberg" fullname="C. Holmberg">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="J." surname="Rosenberg" fullname="J. Rosenberg">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2018" month="July"/>
            <abstract>
              <t indent="0">This document describes a protocol for Network Address Translator (NAT) traversal for UDP-based communication.  This protocol is called Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE).  ICE makes use of the Session Traversal Utilities for NAT (STUN) protocol and its extension, Traversal Using Relay NAT (TURN).</t>
              <t indent="0">This document obsoletes RFC 5245.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8445"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8445"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC8825" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8825" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8825">
          <front>
            <title>Overview: Real-Time Protocols for Browser-Based Applications</title>
            <author initials="H." surname="Alvestrand" fullname="Harald T. Alvestrand">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date month="January" year="2021"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8825"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8825"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC8835" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8835" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8835">
          <front>
            <title>Transports for WebRTC</title>
            <author initials="H." surname="Alvestrand" fullname="Harald Alvestrand">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date month="January" year="2021"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8835"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8835"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="authors-addresses" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-appendix.a">
      <name slugifiedName="name-authors-address">Author's Address</name>
      <author initials="M." surname="Thomson" fullname="Martin Thomson">
        <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Mozilla</organization>
        <address>
          <postal/>
          <email>martin.thomson@gmail.com</email>
        </address>
      </author>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
