<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="3" category="info" consensus="true" docName="draft-ietf-iasa2-rfc5377bis-03" indexInclude="true" ipr="trust200902" number="8721" obsoletes="5377" prepTime="2020-02-26T17:10:45" scripts="Common,Latin" sortRefs="true" submissionType="IETF" symRefs="true" tocDepth="3" tocInclude="true" xml:lang="en">
  <link href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-iasa2-rfc5377bis-03" rel="prev"/>
  <link href="https://dx.doi.org/10.17487/rfc8721" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="urn:issn:2070-1721" rel="alternate"/>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Outbound Rights Advice">Advice to the Trustees of the IETF Trust on Rights to Be Granted in IETF Documents</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8721" stream="IETF"/>
    <author fullname="Joel M. Halpern" initials="J." role="editor" surname="Halpern">
      <organization abbrev="Ericsson" showOnFrontPage="true">Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>P. O. Box 6049</street>
          <city>Leesburg</city>
          <region>VA</region>
          <code>20178</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>joel.halpern@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="02" year="2020"/>
    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>IASA2</workgroup>
    <keyword>IASA</keyword>
    <keyword>Trust</keyword>
    <abstract pn="section-abstract">
      <t pn="section-abstract-1">Contributors grant intellectual property rights to the IETF.  The
      IETF Trust holds and manages those rights on behalf of the IETF.  The
      Trustees of the IETF Trust are responsible for that management.  This
      management includes granting the licenses to copy, implement, and
      otherwise use IETF Contributions, among them Internet-Drafts and RFCs.
      The Trustees of the IETF Trust accept direction from the IETF regarding
      the rights to be granted. This document describes the desires of the
      IETF regarding outbound rights to be granted in IETF
      Contributions. This document obsoletes RFC 5377 solely for the
      purpose of removing references to the IETF Administrative Oversight Committee 
      (IAOC), which was part of the IETF Administrative Support Activity (IASA).</t>
    </abstract>
    <boilerplate>
      <section anchor="status-of-memo" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-boilerplate.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-status-of-this-memo">Status of This Memo</name>
        <t pn="section-boilerplate.1-1">
            This document is not an Internet Standards Track specification; it is
            published for informational purposes.  
        </t>
        <t pn="section-boilerplate.1-2">
            This document is a product of the Internet Engineering Task Force
            (IETF).  It represents the consensus of the IETF community.  It has
            received public review and has been approved for publication by the
            Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG).  Not all documents
            approved by the IESG are candidates for any level of Internet
            Standard; see Section 2 of RFC 7841. 
        </t>
        <t pn="section-boilerplate.1-3">
            Information about the current status of this document, any
            errata, and how to provide feedback on it may be obtained at
            <eref target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8721" brackets="none"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="copyright" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-boilerplate.2">
        <name slugifiedName="name-copyright-notice">Copyright Notice</name>
        <t pn="section-boilerplate.2-1">
            Copyright (c) 2020 IETF Trust and the persons identified as the
            document authors. All rights reserved.
        </t>
        <t pn="section-boilerplate.2-2">
            This document is subject to BCP 78 and the IETF Trust's Legal
            Provisions Relating to IETF Documents
            (<eref target="https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info" brackets="none"/>) in effect on the date of
            publication of this document. Please review these documents
            carefully, as they describe your rights and restrictions with
            respect to this document. Code Components extracted from this
            document must include Simplified BSD License text as described in
            Section 4.e of the Trust Legal Provisions and are provided without
            warranty as described in the Simplified BSD License.
        </t>
      </section>
    </boilerplate>
    <toc>
      <section anchor="toc" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-toc.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-table-of-contents">Table of Contents</name>
        <ul bare="true" empty="true" indent="2" spacing="compact" pn="section-toc.1-1">
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.1">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.1.1"><xref derivedContent="1" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-1"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-introduction">Introduction</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.1"><xref derivedContent="2" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-purpose-in-granting-rights">Purpose in Granting Rights</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.3">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.3.1"><xref derivedContent="3" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-3"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-powers-and-authority">Powers and Authority</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.4">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.4.1"><xref derivedContent="4" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-4"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-recommended-grants-of-right">Recommended Grants of Right to Copy</xref></t>
            <ul bare="true" empty="true" indent="2" spacing="compact" pn="section-toc.1-1.4.2">
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.4.2.1">
                <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.4.2.1.1"><xref derivedContent="4.1" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-4.1"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-rights-granted-for-reproduc">Rights Granted for Reproduction of RFCs</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.4.2.2">
                <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.4.2.2.1"><xref derivedContent="4.2" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-4.2"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-rights-granted-for-quoting-">Rights Granted for Quoting from IETF Contributions</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.4.2.3">
                <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.4.2.3.1"><xref derivedContent="4.3" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-4.3"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-rights-granted-for-implemen">Rights Granted for Implementing Based on IETF Contributions</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.4.2.4">
                <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.4.2.4.1"><xref derivedContent="4.4" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-4.4"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-rights-granted-for-use-of-t">Rights Granted for Use of Text from IETF Contributions</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.4.2.5">
                <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.4.2.5.1"><xref derivedContent="4.5" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-4.5"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-additional-licenses-for-iet">Additional Licenses for IETF Contributions</xref></t>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.5">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.5.1"><xref derivedContent="5" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-5"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-iana-considerations">IANA Considerations</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.6">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.6.1"><xref derivedContent="6" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-6"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-security-considerations">Security Considerations</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.7">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.7.1"><xref derivedContent="7" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-7"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-references">References</xref></t>
            <ul bare="true" empty="true" indent="2" spacing="compact" pn="section-toc.1-1.7.2">
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.7.2.1">
                <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.7.2.1.1"><xref derivedContent="7.1" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-7.1"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-normative-references">Normative References</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.7.2.2">
                <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.7.2.2.1"><xref derivedContent="7.2" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-7.2"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-informative-references">Informative References</xref></t>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.8">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.8.1"><xref derivedContent="" format="none" sectionFormat="of" target="section-appendix.a"/><xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-authors-address">Author's Address</xref></t>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </toc>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-1">
      <name slugifiedName="name-introduction">Introduction</name>
      <t pn="section-1-1">Under the current operational and administrative structures, IETF
      intellectual property rights are vested in the IETF Trust administered
      by a board of trustees.  This includes the right to make use of IETF
      Contributions, as granted by Contributors under the rules laid out in
      <xref target="RFC5378" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC5378"/>. The Trustees of the IETF Trust
      are  therefore responsible for defining the rights to copy granted by
      the IETF to people who wish to make use of the material in these
      documents.</t>
      <t pn="section-1-2">For consistency and clarity, this document uses the same terminology
      laid out in <xref target="RFC5378" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC5378"/> and uses the same
      meanings as defined in that document.</t>
      <t pn="section-1-3">The IETF Trust, by way of its Trustees, has indicated, as is
      consistent with the IETF structure,
      that it will respect the wishes of the IETF in regard to what these
      granted rights ought to be. It is therefore the IETF's responsibility to
      articulate those wishes. This document represents the wishes of the IETF
      regarding the rights granted to all users in regard to IETF
      Contributions, until it is superseded.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Purpose" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-2">
      <name slugifiedName="name-purpose-in-granting-rights">Purpose in Granting Rights</name>
      <t pn="section-2-1">In providing a description of the wishes of the IETF with regard to
      rights granted in RFCs, it is helpful to keep in mind the purpose of
      granting such rights.</t>
      <t pn="section-2-2">The mission of the IETF is to produce documents that make the Internet
      work better (see <xref target="RFC3935" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC3935"/> for more details).  These
      documents, when completed, are published as RFCs.</t>
      <t pn="section-2-3">An important subclass of RFCs is standards describing protocols; for
      these, the primary value to the Internet is the ability of implementors
      to build solutions (products, software, etc.) that interoperate using
      these standards. Hence, the IETF has a strong interest in seeing
      accurate, interoperable implementations of the material 
      the IETF publishes. The IETF Trust
      grants rights to copy to people to make use of the text in the RFCs in
      order to encourage accurate and interoperable implementations.</t>
      <t pn="section-2-4">As early
      implementations from Internet-Drafts make use of descriptions in those
      Internet-Drafts, similar desires apply to Internet-Drafts.</t>
      <t pn="section-2-5">Similar considerations also apply to non-standard,
      non-protocol documents such as BCP (Best Current Practice) and
      Informational documents; in this document, we recommend a common
      approach to the issue of right-to-use licenses for all IETF
      documents.</t>
      <t pn="section-2-6">Previous documents regarding rights in IETF documents have included
      in the RFC text specific text to be used to achieve the stated goals.  
      This has proved problematic. When problems are found with such text,
      even when the problem is not a change in intent, it is necessary to 
      revise the RFC to fix the problem.  At best, this delays fixing legal
      issues that need prompt attention.  As such, this document describes
      the IETF desires to the Trustees of the IETF Trust, but does not
      provide the specific legal wording to address the goals.  The selection,
      and updating as necessary, of legal wording is left to the Trustees of
      the IETF Trust.</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-3">
      <name slugifiedName="name-powers-and-authority">Powers and Authority</name>
      <t pn="section-3-1">As described in the introduction, and formally specified in
      <xref target="RFC5378" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC5378"/>, the legal authority for determining
      and granting users rights to copy material in RFCs and other IETF 
      Contributions rests with the Trustees for the IETF
      Trust. This
      document provides guidance to that body, based on the rough consensus of
      the IETF. The Trustees of the IETF Trust have the
      authority and responsibility to determine the exact text insertions
      (or other mechanisms), if any, needed in
      Internet-Drafts, RFCs, and all IETF Contributions to meet these
      goals.  The IETF Trust License Policy is available from
      <xref target="TRUST-LEGAL" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="TRUST-LEGAL"/>
        <eref target="https://trustee.ietf.org/docs/IETF-Trust-License-Policy.pdf" brackets="angle"/>.</t>
      <t pn="section-3-2">To ensure continuity, the starting point for license text and other
      materials will be that previously created by the Trustees of the IETF
      under the authority of <xref target="RFC5377" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC5377"/> which this
      document supersedes.  Changes to the IETF documentation, and document
      policies themselves, take effect as determined by the Trustees of the
      IETF Trust.</t>
      <t pn="section-3-3">This document does not specify what rights the IETF Trust
      receives from others in IETF Contributions. That is left to another
      document (<xref target="RFC5378" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC5378"/>).  While care has been
      taken by the working group in developing this document, 
      and care will be taken by the Trustees of the IETF Trust,
      to see that sufficient rights are granted to the IETF Trust in IETF
      Contributions, it is also the case that the Trust can not grant rights
      it has not or does not receive, and it is expected that policies will be
      in line with that fact. Similarly, the rights granted for pre-existing
      documents can not be expanded unless the holders of rights in those 
      Contributions choose to grant expanded rights. Nonetheless, to the
      degree it can, and without
      embarking on a massive effort, it is desirable if similar rights to
      those described below can be granted in older RFCs.</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-4">
      <name slugifiedName="name-recommended-grants-of-right">Recommended Grants of Right to Copy</name>
      <t pn="section-4-1">The IETF grants rights to copy and modify parts of IETF Contributions
      in order to meet the objectives described earlier. As such, different
      circumstances and different parts of documents may need different
      grants. This section contains subsections for each such different grant
      that is currently envisioned. Each section is intended to describe a
      particular usage, to describe how that usage is recognizable, and to
      provide guidance to the Trustees of the IETF Trust as to what rights
      the IETF would like to see granted in that circumstance and what
      limitations should be put on such granting.</t>
      <t pn="section-4-2">These recommendations for outgoing rights are structured around the
      assumptions documented in <xref target="RFC5378" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC5378"/>.  Thus,
      this document is about granting rights derived from those granted to the
      IETF Trust. The recommendations below are how those granted rights should
      in turn be passed on to others using IETF documents in ways and for
      purposes that fit with the goals of the IETF.  This discussion
      is also separate from discussion of the rights the IETF itself requires
      in documents
      to do its job, as those are not "outbound" rights. It is expected that
      the rights granted to the IETF will be a superset of those copying
      rights we wish to grant to others.</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-4.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-rights-granted-for-reproduc">Rights Granted for Reproduction of RFCs</name>
        <t pn="section-4.1-1">It has long been IETF policy to encourage copying of RFCs in full.
        This permits wide dissemination of the material, without risking loss
        of context or meaning. The IETF wishes to continue to permit anyone to
        make full copies and translations of RFCs.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-4.2">
        <name slugifiedName="name-rights-granted-for-quoting-">Rights Granted for Quoting from IETF Contributions</name>
        <t pn="section-4.2-1">There is rough consensus that it is useful to permit quoting
        without modification of excerpts from IETF Contributions. Such
        excerpts may be of any length and in any context. Translation of
        quotations is also to be permitted. All such quotations should be
        attributed properly to the IETF and the IETF Contribution from which
        they are taken.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-4.3">
        <name slugifiedName="name-rights-granted-for-implemen">Rights Granted for Implementing Based on IETF Contributions</name>
        <t pn="section-4.3-1">IETF Contributions often include components intended to be directly
        processed by a computer. Examples of these include ABNF definitions,
        XML Schemas, XML DTDs, XML RelaxNG definitions, tables of values,
        MIBs, ASN.1, and classical programming code. These are included
        in IETF Contributions for clarity and precision in specification. It
        is clearly beneficial, when such items are included in IETF
        Contributions, to permit the inclusion of such code components in
        products that implement the Contribution. It has been pointed out
        that in several important contexts, use of such code requires the
        ability to modify the code. One common example of this is simply the
        need to adapt code for use in specific contexts (languages, compilers,
        tool systems, etc.) Such use frequently requires some changes to the
        text of the code from the IETF Contribution. Another example is that
        code included in open source products is frequently licensed to permit
        any and all of the code to be modified. Since we want this code
        included in such products, it follows that we need to permit such
        modification. While there has been discussion of restricting
        in some way the rights to make such modifications, the rough consensus
        of the IETF is
        that such restrictions are likely a bad idea, and are certainly very
        complex to define.</t>
        <t pn="section-4.3-2"> As such, the rough consensus is that the IETF Trust is to grant
        rights such that code components of IETF Contributions can be
        extracted, modified, and used by anyone in any way desired.  To
        enable the broadest possible extraction, modification, and usage,
        the IETF Trust should avoid adding software license obligations
        beyond those already present in a Contribution.  The granted
        rights to extract, modify, and use code should allow creation
        of derived works outside the IETF that may carry additional
        license obligations.  As the IETF Trust can not grant rights
        it does not receive, the rights to extract, modify, and use code
        described in this paragraph can not be granted in IETF
        Contributions that are explicitly marked as not permitting
        derivative works.</t>
        <t pn="section-4.3-3">While it is up to the Trustees of the IETF Trust to determine the
        best way of meeting
        this objective, two mechanisms are suggested here that are believed to
        be helpful in documenting the intended grant to readers and users of
        IETF Contributions.</t>
        <t pn="section-4.3-4">Firstly, the Trustees of the IETF Trust should maintain, in a
        suitable, easily accessible
        fashion, a list of common RFC components that will be considered to
        be code. To start, this list should include at least the items listed
        above. The Trustees of the IETF Trust will add to this list as
        they deem suitable or as they are directed by the IETF.</t>
        <t pn="section-4.3-5">Additionally, the Trustees of the IETF Trust should define a
        textual representation to
        be included in an IETF Contribution to indicate that a portion of the
        document is considered by the authors (and later, the working group,
        and upon approval, the IETF) to be code and thus subject to the
        permissions granted to use code.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-4.4">
        <name slugifiedName="name-rights-granted-for-use-of-t">Rights Granted for Use of Text from IETF Contributions</name>
        <t pn="section-4.4-1">There is no consensus at this time to permit the use of text from
        RFCs in contexts where the right to modify the text is required. The
        authors of IETF Contributions may be able and willing to grant such
        rights independently of the rights they have granted to the IETF by
        making the Contribution.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-4.5">
        <name slugifiedName="name-additional-licenses-for-iet">Additional Licenses for IETF Contributions</name>
        <t pn="section-4.5-1">There have been contexts where the material in an IETF Contribution
        is also available under other license terms. The IETF wishes to be
        able to include content that is available under such licenses. It is
        desirable to indicate in the IETF Contribution that other licenses are
        available. It would be inappropriate and confusing if such additional
        licenses restricted the rights the IETF intends to grant in the
        content of RFCs.</t>
        <t pn="section-4.5-2">However, the IETF does not wish to have IETF Contributions contain
        additional licenses, as that introduces a number
        of additional difficulties. 
        Specifically, additional text in the document, and any additional
        license referred to by permitted additional text, must not in any way
        restrict the rights the IETF intends to grant to others for using the
        contents of IETF Contributions.</t>
        <t pn="section-4.5-3">Authors of Contributions retain all rights in their Contributions.
        As such, an author may directly grant any rights they wish separately
        from what the IETF grants. However, a reader wishing to determine or
        make use of such grants will need to either consult external sources of
        information, possibly including
        open source code and documents, or contact the author directly.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-5">
      <name slugifiedName="name-iana-considerations">IANA Considerations</name>
      <t pn="section-5-1">No values are assigned in this document, no registries are created,
      and there is no action assigned to the IANA by this document. One list
      (of kinds of code sections) is anticipated, to be created and maintained
      by the Trustees of the IETF Trust. It is up to the Trustees of the IETF
      Trust whether they create such a list and
      whether they choose to involve the IANA in maintaining that list.</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-6">
      <name slugifiedName="name-security-considerations">Security Considerations</name>
      <t pn="section-6-1">This document introduces no new security considerations. It is a
      process document about the IETF's IPR rights being granted to other
      people. While there may be attacks against the integrity or
      effectiveness of the IETF processes, this document does not address such
      issues.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references pn="section-7">
      <name slugifiedName="name-references">References</name>
      <references pn="section-7.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-normative-references">Normative References</name>
        <reference anchor="RFC5377" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5377" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC5377">
          <front>
            <title>Advice to the Trustees of the IETF Trust on Rights to Be Granted in IETF Documents</title>
            <author initials="J." surname="Halpern" fullname="J. Halpern" role="editor">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2008" month="November"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>Contributors grant intellectual property rights to the IETF.  The IETF Trust holds and manages those rights on behalf of the IETF.  The Trustees of the IETF Trust are responsible for that management.  This management includes granting the licenses to copy, implement, and otherwise use IETF Contributions, among them Internet-Drafts and RFCs.  The Trustees of the IETF Trust accepts direction from the IETF regarding the rights to be granted.  This document describes the desires of the IETF regarding outbound rights to be granted in IETF Contributions.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5377"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC5377"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC5378" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5378" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC5378">
          <front>
            <title>Rights Contributors Provide to the IETF Trust</title>
            <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="S. Bradner" role="editor">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="J." surname="Contreras" fullname="J. Contreras" role="editor">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2008" month="November"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>The IETF policies about rights in Contributions to the IETF are designed to ensure that such Contributions can be made available to the IETF and Internet communities while permitting the authors to retain as many rights as possible.  This memo details the IETF policies on rights in Contributions to the IETF.  It also describes the objectives that the policies are designed to meet.  This memo obsoletes RFCs 3978 and 4748 and, with BCP 79 and RFC 5377, replaces Section 10 of RFC 2026.  This document  specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="78"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5378"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC5378"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
      <references pn="section-7.2">
        <name slugifiedName="name-informative-references">Informative References</name>
        <reference anchor="RFC3935" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3935" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC3935">
          <front>
            <title>A Mission Statement for the IETF</title>
            <author initials="H." surname="Alvestrand" fullname="H. Alvestrand">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2004" month="October"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>This memo gives a mission statement for the IETF, tries to define the terms used in the statement sufficiently to make the mission statement understandable and useful, argues why the IETF needs a mission statement, and tries to capture some of the debate that led to this point.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="95"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3935"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC3935"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="TRUST-LEGAL" target="http://trustee.ietf.org/docs/IETF-Trust-License-Policy.pdf" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="TRUST-LEGAL">
          <front>
            <title>Legal Provisions Relating to IETF Documents</title>
            <author>
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true">IETF Trust</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="March" year="2015"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="authors-addresses" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-appendix.a">
      <name slugifiedName="name-authors-address">Author's Address</name>
      <author fullname="Joel M. Halpern" initials="J." role="editor" surname="Halpern">
        <organization abbrev="Ericsson" showOnFrontPage="true">Ericsson</organization>
        <address>
          <postal>
            <street>P. O. Box 6049</street>
            <city>Leesburg</city>
            <region>VA</region>
            <code>20178</code>
            <country>United States of America</country>
          </postal>
          <email>joel.halpern@ericsson.com</email>
        </address>
      </author>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
