<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="3" category="info" docName="draft-ise-iana-policy-04" indexInclude="true" ipr="trust200902" number="8726" prepTime="2020-11-19T13:33:31" scripts="Common,Latin" sortRefs="true" submissionType="independent" symRefs="true" tocDepth="3" tocInclude="true" xml:lang="en">
  <link href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ise-iana-policy-04" rel="prev"/>
  <link href="https://dx.doi.org/10.17487/rfc8726" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="urn:issn:2070-1721" rel="alternate"/>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IANA and the Independent Stream">How Requests for IANA Action Will Be Handled on the Independent Stream</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8726" stream="independent"/>
    <author fullname="Adrian Farrel" initials="A." surname="Farrel">
      <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Independent Submissions Editor</organization>
      <address>
        <email>rfc-ise@rfc-editor.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="11" year="2020"/>
    <area/>
    <workgroup/>
    <keyword>IANA</keyword>
    <keyword>Independent Submission Stream</keyword>
    <keyword>ISE</keyword>
    <abstract pn="section-abstract">
      <t indent="0" pn="section-abstract-1">The Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA) maintains registries
      to track code points used
         by protocols such as those defined by the IETF and documented in RFCs developed on the IETF
         Stream.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-abstract-2">The Independent Submission Stream is another source of documents that can be published as
         RFCs.  This stream is under the care of the Independent Submissions Editor (ISE).</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-abstract-3">This document complements RFC 4846 by providing a description of how the ISE currently
         handles documents in the Independent Submission Stream that request actions from IANA.
         Nothing in this document changes existing IANA registries or their allocation policies, nor
         does it change any previously documented processes.</t>
    </abstract>
    <boilerplate>
      <section anchor="status-of-memo" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-boilerplate.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-status-of-this-memo">Status of This Memo</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.1-1">
            This document is not an Internet Standards Track specification; it is
            published for informational purposes.
        </t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.1-2">
            This is a contribution to the RFC Series, independently of any
            other RFC stream.  The RFC Editor has chosen to publish this
            document at its discretion and makes no statement about its value
            for implementation or deployment.  Documents approved for
            publication by the RFC Editor are not candidates for any level of
            Internet Standard; see Section 2 of RFC 7841.
        </t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.1-3">
            Information about the current status of this document, any
            errata, and how to provide feedback on it may be obtained at
            <eref target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8726" brackets="none"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="copyright" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-boilerplate.2">
        <name slugifiedName="name-copyright-notice">Copyright Notice</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.2-1">
            Copyright (c) 2020 IETF Trust and the persons identified as the
            document authors. All rights reserved.
        </t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.2-2">
            This document is subject to BCP 78 and the IETF Trust's Legal
            Provisions Relating to IETF Documents
            (<eref target="https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info" brackets="none"/>) in effect on the date of
            publication of this document. Please review these documents
            carefully, as they describe your rights and restrictions with
            respect to this document.
        </t>
      </section>
    </boilerplate>
    <toc>
      <section anchor="toc" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-toc.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-table-of-contents">Table of Contents</name>
        <ul bare="true" empty="true" indent="2" spacing="compact" pn="section-toc.1-1">
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.1">
            <t indent="0" keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.1.1"><xref derivedContent="1" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-1"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-introduction">Introduction</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2">
            <t indent="0" keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.1"><xref derivedContent="2" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-allocations-from-existing-r">Allocations from Existing Registries</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.3">
            <t indent="0" keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.3.1"><xref derivedContent="3" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-3"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-changing-policies-of-existi">Changing Policies of Existing Registries</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.4">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.4.1"><xref derivedContent="4" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-4"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-creating-new-iana-registrie">Creating New IANA Registries</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.5">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.5.1"><xref derivedContent="5" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-5"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-assigning-designated-expert">Assigning Designated Experts</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.6">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.6.1"><xref derivedContent="6" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-6"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-transfer-of-control">Transfer of Control</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.7">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.7.1"><xref derivedContent="7" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-7"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-iana-considerations">IANA Considerations</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.8">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.8.1"><xref derivedContent="8" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-8"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-security-considerations">Security Considerations</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.9">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.9.1"><xref derivedContent="9" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-9"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-references">References</xref></t>
            <ul bare="true" empty="true" indent="2" spacing="compact" pn="section-toc.1-1.9.2">
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.9.2.1">
                <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.9.2.1.1"><xref derivedContent="9.1" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-9.1"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-normative-references">Normative References</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.9.2.2">
                <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.9.2.2.1"><xref derivedContent="9.2" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-9.2"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-informative-references">Informative References</xref></t>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.10">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.10.1"><xref derivedContent="" format="none" sectionFormat="of" target="section-appendix.a"/><xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.11">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.11.1"><xref derivedContent="" format="none" sectionFormat="of" target="section-appendix.b"/><xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-authors-address">Author's Address</xref></t>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </toc>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-1">
      <name slugifiedName="name-introduction">Introduction</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-1">The Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA) maintains registries
      to track code points used
         by protocols such as those defined by the IETF and documented in RFCs developed on the IETF Stream.
         A full list of registries and code points can be found at
         <eref target="https://www.iana.org/protocols" brackets="none"/>.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-2">Requests may be made to IANA for actions to create registries or to allocate code points from
         existing registries.  Procedures for these operations are described in <xref target="RFC8126" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8126"/>.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-3">Many requests for IANA action are included in documents that are progressed for publication as RFCs.
         RFCs may be sourced from within the IETF (on the IETF Stream) but may also be sourced from other
         streams, including the Independent Submission Stream (the Independent Stream), as described in
         <xref target="RFC4846" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC4846"/>.  The Independent Stream is under the care of the Independent Submissions Editor
         (ISE).</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-4">This document complements <xref target="RFC4846" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC4846"/> by providing a description of how the ISE
         currently handles documents in the Independent Stream that request actions from IANA.  Nothing
         in this document changes existing IANA registries or their allocation policies, nor does it change
         any previously documented processes.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-5">If a case arises that is not precisely covered by this document, the ISE may discuss
         a solution with the interested parties, including IANA, the IESG, the stream managers for other streams,
         and the authors of an Independent Submission that requests IANA action.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="exist" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-2">
      <name slugifiedName="name-allocations-from-existing-r">Allocations from Existing Registries</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-2-1">Each IANA registry is governed by an allocation policy -- the rules that IANA applies to determine
         which code points can be allocated and under what circumstances.  These policies are described in
         <xref target="RFC8126" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8126"/>.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-2-2">Documents proceeding from the Independent Stream will always follow the assignment policies defined
         for the registries from which they request allocations.  Similarly, all code point assignments are
         subject to the oversight of any designated expert (DE) appointed for the registry.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-2-3">It should be noted that documents on the Independent Stream can never result in Standards Track
         RFCs and Independent Stream documents are never subject to IETF review.  Thus, a registry whose
         policy is "IETF Review" or "Standards Action" <xref target="RFC8126" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8126"/> is not available to Independent Stream
         documents.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="change" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-3">
      <name slugifiedName="name-changing-policies-of-existi">Changing Policies of Existing Registries</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-1">From time to time, a decision is made to change the allocation policy for a registry.  Such changes
          are normally only made using the allocation policy of the registry itself and usually require documentation
          from the same stream that created the registry.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-2">Independent Stream RFCs will not seek to change the allocation policies of any registries except
          those created by documents from the Independent Stream.  The list of such registries is itself
          very limited (see <xref target="new" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="Section 4"/>).</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="new" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-4">
      <name slugifiedName="name-creating-new-iana-registrie">Creating New IANA Registries</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-1">Sometimes registries are needed to track a new set of code points for a new protocol or an extension to an existing protocol.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-2">In general, documents on the Independent Stream cannot request the
   creation of a new IANA registry.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-3">The only exception to this rule is when a document to be published in
   the Independent Submission Stream requests the allocation of a code
   point from an existing registry with the allocation policy Specification
   Required, Expert Review, RFC Required, or First Come First Served.
   Then the document to be published may also need to create a registry
   that is tied to that specific code point and is used for
   interpreting a sub-code.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-4">Consider, for example, the "Uniform Resource Identifier (URI)
   Schemes" registry <xref target="URL-URIschemes" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="URL-URIschemes"/>.  From time to time, a URI scheme
   may need a registry of associated parameters; for example, consider
   the tel URI scheme that has a register of parameters called the "tel
   URI Parameters" <xref target="URL-telURI" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="URL-telURI"/>.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-5">Such examples are rare and only exist to support the allocation from
   the base registry.  In such cases, where there is an appointed DE for
   the existing base registry, the assignment of the individual code
   point from the existing base registry and the creation of the new
   registry can only happen if the DE approves both actions.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-6">There are several further constraints on the new registry:</t>
      <ul bare="false" empty="false" indent="3" spacing="normal" pn="section-4-7">
        <li pn="section-4-7.1">The allocation policy for the new registry may only be First Come
      First Served, RFC Required, Experimental, or Private Use.  In
      particular, no registry may be created that would require IETF
      action to achieve a future code point allocation.  See <xref target="de" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="Section 5"/> for an explanation of why the application of Specification
      Required and Expert Review are not acceptable policies for any
      registry created from a document in the Independent Stream.</li>
        <li pn="section-4-7.2">If the allocation policy for the new registry is First Come First Served,
the document must contain a brief statement and explanation of the expected arrival rate of new registrations over time.</li>
        <li pn="section-4-7.3">The new registry must contain a clear statement of the escalation
      process for any issues that arise with the registry.  A model for
      this statement is as follows:</li>
      </ul>
      <blockquote pn="section-4-8">
This registry was created by [RFCXXXX], which was published on
         the Independent Submission Stream.  Any issues that arise with
         the management of this registry will be resolved by IANA in
         consultation with the Independent Submissions Editor.</blockquote>
      <ul bare="false" empty="false" indent="3" spacing="normal" pn="section-4-9">
        <li pn="section-4-9.1">The IESG will be invited to provide its opinions about the
      advisability of the creation of any new registries during its
      conflict review of the document <xref target="RFC5742" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC5742"/>, and the ISE will give
      full consideration to such opinions.</li>
      </ul>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-10">
   Authors of Independent Submission Stream documents should consider
   the most appropriate venue to host such registries, taking into
   account where the expertise for managing and reviewing registry
   assignments may be found.  In some cases, this may mean that
   registries are hosted by organizations other than IANA.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="de" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-5">
      <name slugifiedName="name-assigning-designated-expert">Assigning Designated Experts</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-5-1">Some IANA allocation policies (specifically, Specification Required and Expert Review) utilize
          the review of a DE.  The procedures applicable to the appointment and actions of a DE are
          described in <xref target="RFC8126" sectionFormat="of" section="5" format="default" derivedLink="https://rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc8126#section-5" derivedContent="RFC8126"/>.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-5-2">When a DE is appointed, the position must be maintained and supported by whoever designated the
          DE in the first place.  That is, someone must appoint replacement DEs if necessary, and someone
          must provide a backstop in case the appointed DEs are unresponsive.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-5-3">The ISE will not appoint a DE.  That means that no subregistry created for Independent Stream
          documents will require the review of a DE.  That means that no new subregistry can be
          created that uses the Specification Required or Expert Review policies.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="tx" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-6">
      <name slugifiedName="name-transfer-of-control">Transfer of Control</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-6-1">Very rarely, it may be desirable to transfer "ownership" of an IANA registry from the Independent
          Stream to the IETF Stream.  This might happen, for example, if a protocol was originally
          documented in the Independent Stream but has been adopted for work and standardization
          in the IETF.  Such a transfer may require an IETF Stream RFC to act as the base reference for the
          registry and will require discussion and agreement with the ISE.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-6-2">Ownership of a registry will not be transferred from the IETF Stream to the Independent Stream.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-7">
      <name slugifiedName="name-iana-considerations">IANA Considerations</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-7-1">This document is all about IANA actions but makes no request for IANA action.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-8">
      <name slugifiedName="name-security-considerations">Security Considerations</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-8-1">There are no direct security considerations arising from this document.  It may be noted that some IANA
         registries relate to security protocols, and the stability and proper management of those registries
         contribute to the stability of the protocols themselves.  That is a benefit for the security of the
         Internet and the users of the Internet.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references pn="section-9">
      <name slugifiedName="name-references">References</name>
      <references pn="section-9.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-normative-references">Normative References</name>
        <reference anchor="RFC4846" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4846" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC4846">
          <front>
            <title>Independent Submissions to the RFC Editor</title>
            <author initials="J." surname="Klensin" fullname="J. Klensin" role="editor">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="D." surname="Thaler" fullname="D. Thaler" role="editor">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2007" month="July"/>
            <abstract>
              <t indent="0">There is a long-standing tradition in the Internet community, predating the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) by many years, of use of the RFC Series to publish materials that are not rooted in the IETF standards process and its review and approval mechanisms. These documents, known as "Independent Submissions", serve a number of important functions for the Internet community, both inside and outside of the community of active IETF participants.  This document discusses the Independent Submission model and some reasons why it is important.  It then describes editorial and processing norms that can be used for Independent Submissions as the community goes forward into new relationships between the IETF community and its primary technical publisher.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4846"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC4846"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC5742" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5742" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC5742">
          <front>
            <title>IESG Procedures for Handling of Independent and IRTF Stream Submissions</title>
            <author initials="H." surname="Alvestrand" fullname="H. Alvestrand">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="R." surname="Housley" fullname="R. Housley">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2009" month="December"/>
            <abstract>
              <t indent="0">This document describes the procedures used by the IESG for handling documents submitted for RFC publication from the Independent Submission and IRTF streams. </t>
              <t indent="0">This document updates procedures described in RFC 2026 and RFC 3710.   This memo documents an Internet Best Current Practice.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="92"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5742"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC5742"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC8126" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8126" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8126">
          <front>
            <title>Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs</title>
            <author initials="M." surname="Cotton" fullname="M. Cotton">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="B." surname="Leiba" fullname="B. Leiba">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="T." surname="Narten" fullname="T. Narten">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2017" month="June"/>
            <abstract>
              <t indent="0">Many protocols make use of points of extensibility that use constants to identify various protocol parameters.  To ensure that the values in these fields do not have conflicting uses and to promote interoperability, their allocations are often coordinated by a central record keeper.  For IETF protocols, that role is filled by the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA).</t>
              <t indent="0">To make assignments in a given registry prudently, guidance describing the conditions under which new values should be assigned, as well as when and how modifications to existing values can be made, is needed.  This document defines a framework for the documentation of these guidelines by specification authors, in order to assure that the provided guidance for the IANA Considerations is clear and addresses the various issues that are likely in the operation of a registry.</t>
              <t indent="0">This is the third edition of this document; it obsoletes RFC 5226.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="26"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8126"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8126"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
      <references pn="section-9.2">
        <name slugifiedName="name-informative-references">Informative References</name>
        <reference anchor="URL-telURI" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/tel-uri-parameters" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="URL-telURI">
          <front>
            <title>tel URI Parameters</title>
            <author>
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="URL-URIschemes" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/uri-schemes" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="URL-URIschemes">
          <front>
            <title>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) Schemes</title>
            <author>
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-appendix.a">
      <name slugifiedName="name-acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.a-1">Thanks to <contact fullname="Brian Carpenter"/>, <contact fullname="Subramanian Moonesamy"/>, <contact fullname="Craig Partridge"/>, <contact fullname="Michelle Cotton"/>, <contact fullname="Andrew       Malis"/>, <contact fullname="Warren Kumari"/>, <contact fullname="Ned       Freed"/>, <contact fullname="Rich Salz"/>, <contact fullname="Michael       Richardson"/>, <contact fullname="Colin Perkins"/>, <contact fullname="Stephen Farrell"/>,
        <contact fullname="Barry Leiba"/>, and <contact fullname="Benjamin  Kaduk"/> for suggestions and advice.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="authors-addresses" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-appendix.b">
      <name slugifiedName="name-authors-address">Author's Address</name>
      <author fullname="Adrian Farrel" initials="A." surname="Farrel">
        <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Independent Submissions Editor</organization>
        <address>
          <email>rfc-ise@rfc-editor.org</email>
        </address>
      </author>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
