<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="3" category="info" consensus="true" docName="draft-ietf-iasa2-rfc6220bis-04" indexInclude="true" ipr="trust200902" number="8722" obsoletes="6220" prepTime="2020-02-26T17:11:27" scripts="Common,Latin" sortRefs="true" submissionType="IAB" symRefs="true" tocDepth="3" tocInclude="true" xml:lang="en">
  <link href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-iasa2-rfc6220bis-04" rel="prev"/>
  <link href="https://dx.doi.org/10.17487/rfc8722" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="urn:issn:2070-1721" rel="alternate"/>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Role of Registry Operators">Defining the Role and Function of IETF Protocol Parameter Registry Operators</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8722" stream="IAB"/>
    <author initials="D." surname="McPherson" fullname="Danny McPherson" role="editor">
      <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Verisign, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>dmcpherson@verisign.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="O." surname="Kolkman" fullname="Olaf Kolkman" role="editor">
      <organization abbrev="ISOC" showOnFrontPage="true">Internet Society</organization>
      <address>
        <email>kolkman@isoc.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="J." surname="Klensin" fullname="John C Klensin" role="editor">
      <address>
        <email>john-ietf@jck.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="G." surname="Huston" fullname="Geoff Huston" role="editor">
      <organization showOnFrontPage="true">APNIC</organization>
      <address>
        <email>gih@apnic.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="02" year="2020"/>
    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Architecture Board (IAB)</workgroup>
    <keyword>IANA</keyword>
    <keyword>Governance</keyword>
    <keyword>IASA</keyword>
    <abstract pn="section-abstract">
      <t pn="section-abstract-1">
	Many Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) protocols make use
	of commonly defined values that are passed in messages or
	packets.  To ensure consistent interpretation of these values
	between independent implementations, there is a need to ensure
	that the values and associated semantic intent are uniquely
	defined.  The IETF uses registry functions to record assigned
	protocol parameter values and their associated semantic
	intentions.  For each IETF protocol parameter, it is current
	practice for the IETF to delegate the role of Protocol
	Parameter Registry Operator to a nominated entity.  This
	document provides a description of, and the requirements for,
	these delegated functions. This document obsoletes RFC 6220 to
	replace all references to the IETF Administrative Support Activity
	(IASA) and related structures with those defined by the IASA 2.0 Model.

      </t>
    </abstract>
    <boilerplate>
      <section anchor="status-of-memo" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-boilerplate.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-status-of-this-memo">Status of This Memo</name>
        <t pn="section-boilerplate.1-1">
            This document is not an Internet Standards Track specification; it is
            published for informational purposes.  
        </t>
        <t pn="section-boilerplate.1-2">
            This document is a product of the Internet Architecture Board
            (IAB) and represents information that the IAB has deemed valuable
            to provide for permanent record.  It represents the consensus of the Internet
            Architecture Board (IAB).  Documents approved for publication
            by the IAB are not candidates for any level of Internet Standard; see
            Section 2 of RFC 7841.
        </t>
        <t pn="section-boilerplate.1-3">
            Information about the current status of this document, any
            errata, and how to provide feedback on it may be obtained at
            <eref target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8722" brackets="none"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="copyright" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-boilerplate.2">
        <name slugifiedName="name-copyright-notice">Copyright Notice</name>
        <t pn="section-boilerplate.2-1">
            Copyright (c) 2020 IETF Trust and the persons identified as the
            document authors. All rights reserved.
        </t>
        <t pn="section-boilerplate.2-2">
            This document is subject to BCP 78 and the IETF Trust's Legal
            Provisions Relating to IETF Documents
            (<eref target="https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info" brackets="none"/>) in effect on the date of
            publication of this document. Please review these documents
            carefully, as they describe your rights and restrictions with
            respect to this document.
        </t>
      </section>
    </boilerplate>
    <toc>
      <section anchor="toc" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-toc.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-table-of-contents">Table of Contents</name>
        <ul bare="true" empty="true" indent="2" spacing="compact" pn="section-toc.1-1">
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.1">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.1.1"><xref derivedContent="1" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-1"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-overview">Overview</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.1"><xref derivedContent="2" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-roles-and-responsibilities-">Roles and Responsibilities Concerning IETF Protocol Parameter Registries</xref></t>
            <ul bare="true" empty="true" indent="2" spacing="compact" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2">
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.1">
                <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.1.1"><xref derivedContent="2.1" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2.1"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-protocol-parameter-registry">Protocol Parameter Registry Operator Role</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.2">
                <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.2.1"><xref derivedContent="2.2" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2.2"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-iab-role">IAB Role</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.3">
                <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.3.1"><xref derivedContent="2.3" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2.3"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-iesg-role">IESG Role</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.4">
                <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.4.1"><xref derivedContent="2.4" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2.4"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-role-of-the-ietf-trust">Role of the IETF Trust</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.5">
                <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.5.1"><xref derivedContent="2.5" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2.5"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-role-of-the-ietf-administra">Role of the IETF Administration Limited         Liability Company</xref></t>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.3">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.3.1"><xref derivedContent="3" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-3"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-miscellaneous-consideration">Miscellaneous Considerations</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.4">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.4.1"><xref derivedContent="4" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-4"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-security-considerations">Security Considerations</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.5">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.5.1"><xref derivedContent="5" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-5"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-iana-considerations">IANA Considerations</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.6">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.6.1"><xref derivedContent="6" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-6"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-informative-references">Informative References</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.7">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.7.1"><xref derivedContent="" format="none" sectionFormat="of" target="section-appendix.a"/><xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-iab-members-at-the-time-of-">IAB Members at the Time of Approval</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.8">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.8.1"><xref derivedContent="" format="none" sectionFormat="of" target="section-appendix.b"/><xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.9">
            <t keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.9.1"><xref derivedContent="" format="none" sectionFormat="of" target="section-appendix.c"/><xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-authors-addresses">Authors' Addresses</xref></t>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </toc>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-1">
      <name slugifiedName="name-overview">Overview</name>
      <t pn="section-1-1">
	
	Many IETF protocols make use of commonly defined values that
	are passed within messages or packets.  To ensure consistent
	interpretation of these values between independent
	implementations, there is a need to ensure that the values
	and associated semantic intent are uniquely defined.  The
	IETF uses registries to record each of the possible values
	of a protocol parameter and their associated semantic
	intent.  These registries, their registration policy, and
	the layout of their content are defined in the so-called
	"IANA Considerations" sections of IETF documents.
      </t>
      <t pn="section-1-2">
	The organizational separation between the IETF and its
	Protocol Parameter Registry Operators parallels ones that are fairly common among
	standards development organizations (SDOs) although less
	common among technology consortia and similar bodies.  These
	functions have been separated into different organizations for
	several reasons.  They include dealing with administrative
	issues, addressing concerns about maintaining an adequate
	distance between basic policy and specific allocations, and
	avoiding any potential conflicts of interest that might arise
	from commercial or organizational relationships.  For example,
	most ISO and ISO/IEC JTC1 standards that require registration
	activities specify a Registration Authority (RA) or
	Maintenance Agency (MA) that, in turn, control the actual
	registration decisions.  The databases of what is registered
	for each standard may then be maintained by a secretariat or
	database function associated with the RA or MA or, less
	frequently, by the secretariat of the body that created and
	maintains the standard itself.
      </t>
      <t pn="section-1-3">
	This structural separation of roles exists within several
	places in the IETF framework (e.g., the RFC Editor
	function).  The Internet Architecture Board (IAB), on behalf
	of the IETF, has the responsibility to define and manage the
	relationship with the Protocol Parameter Registry Operator role.  This
	responsibility includes the selection and management of the
	Protocol Parameter Registry Operator, as well as management
	of the parameter registration process and the guidelines for
	parameter allocation.
      </t>
      <t pn="section-1-4">
	As with other SDOs, although it may delegate authority for
	some specific decisions, the IETF asserts authority and
	responsibility for the management of all of its protocol
	parameters and their registries, even while it generally
	remains isolated from the selection of particular values once
	a registration is approved.  This document describes the
	function of these registries as they apply to individual
	protocol parameters defined by the IETF Internet Standards
	Process (see RFC 6410 <xref target="BCP9" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="BCP9"/>) to allow for an orderly implementation by
	the IETF Administration Limited Liability Company (IETF LLC),
	and others as needed, under guidance from the IAB. This
	document obsoletes RFC 6220 to replace all references to the
	IASA and related structures with those defined by the IASA 2.0
	Model <xref target="RFC8711" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8711"/>.

      </t>
      <t pn="section-1-5">
	Below we provide a description of the requirements for these
	delegated functions, which the IETF traditionally refers to as
	the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA) function.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-2">
      <name slugifiedName="name-roles-and-responsibilities-">Roles and Responsibilities Concerning IETF Protocol Parameter Registries</name>
      <t pn="section-2-1">
	The IETF's longstanding practice is to outsource the
	management and implementation of some important functions
	(e.g., <xref target="RFC8728" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8728"/>).  The protocol parameter
	registry function falls into this category of outsourced
	functions, and what follows here is the description of the
	roles and responsibilities with respect to the registration of
	IETF protocol parameters.
      </t>
      <t pn="section-2-2">
	Specifically, this document describes the operation and role
	of a delegated IETF Protocol Parameter Registry Operator, to 
	be selected and administered by the IETF Administrative
	Support Activity (IASA) <xref target="RFC8711" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8711"/>.  While there is generally a
	single Protocol Parameter Registry Operator, additional
	Operators may be selected to implement specific registries,
	and that has been done occasionally.  Having a single Protocol Parameter Registry Operator
	facilitates coordination among registries, even those that are
	not obviously related, and also makes it easier to have
	consistency of formats and registry structure, which aids
	users of the registries and assists with quality control.
      </t>
      <t pn="section-2-3">
	Many protocols make use of identifiers consisting of constants
	and other well-known values.  Even after a protocol has been
	defined and deployment has begun, new values may need to be
	assigned (e.g., for a new option type in DHCP, or a new
	encryption or authentication algorithm for IPsec).  To ensure
	that such quantities have consistent values and
	interpretations in different implementations, their assignment
	must be administered by a central authority.  For IETF
	protocols, that role is provided by a delegated Protocol
	Parameter Registry Operator.  For any particular protocol
	parameter there is a single delegated Registry Operator.
      </t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="include" anchor="protocolparamreg" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-2.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-protocol-parameter-registry">Protocol Parameter Registry Operator Role</name>
        <t pn="section-2.1-1">
	  The IETF Protocol Parameter Registry function is undertaken
	  under the auspices of the Internet Architecture Board.
        </t>
        <t pn="section-2.1-2">
	  The roles of the Protocol Parameter Registry Operator (Registry Operator) are as
	  follows:
        </t>
        <ul spacing="normal" bare="false" empty="false" pn="section-2.1-3">
          <li pn="section-2.1-3.1">
            <t pn="section-2.1-3.1.1">Review and Advise
            </t>
            <ul spacing="normal" bare="false" empty="false" pn="section-2.1-3.1.2">
              <li pn="section-2.1-3.1.2.1">
		A Registry Operator may be requested to review
		Internet-Drafts that are being considered by the
		Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG), with the
		objective of offering advice to the IESG regarding the
		contents of the "IANA Considerations" section, whether
		such a section, when required, is clear in terms of
		direction to the Registry Operator, and whether the
		section is consistent with the current published
		Registry Operator guidelines.
	      </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-2.1-3.2">
            <t pn="section-2.1-3.2.1">Registry
            </t>
            <ul spacing="normal" bare="false" empty="false" pn="section-2.1-3.2.2">
              <li pn="section-2.1-3.2.2.1">
	      To operate a registry of protocol parameter
	      assignments.
	    </li>
              <li pn="section-2.1-3.2.2.2">
                <t pn="section-2.1-3.2.2.2.1">
	      The delegated Registry Operator registers values for
	      Internet protocol parameters only as directed by the
	      criteria and procedures specified in RFCs, including
	      Standards Track documents <xref target="BCP9" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="BCP9"/>, Best
	      Current Practice documents, and other RFCs that
	      require protocol parameter assignment.

                </t>
                <t pn="section-2.1-3.2.2.2.2">

	      If values for Internet protocol parameters were not
	      specified, or in case of ambiguity, the Registry
	      Operator will continue to assign and register only
	      those protocol parameters that have already been
	      delegated to the Registry Operator, following past and current
	      practice for such assignments, unless otherwise
	      directed in terms of operating practice by the IESG.
	      In the case of ambiguity, the Registry Operator is
	      expected to identify the ambiguity to the IAB or IESG
	      as appropriate and either suggest better text or ask
	      the appropriate parties for clarification.
                </t>
              </li>
            </ul>
            <ul spacing="normal" bare="false" empty="false" pn="section-2.1-3.2.3">
              <li pn="section-2.1-3.2.3.1">
                <t pn="section-2.1-3.2.3.1.1">
	      For each protocol parameter, the associated registry includes:
                </t>
                <ul spacing="normal" bare="false" empty="false" pn="section-2.1-3.2.3.1.2">
                  <li pn="section-2.1-3.2.3.1.2.1">
		  a reference to the RFC document that describes the parameter
		  and the associated "IANA Considerations" concerning the
		  parameter, and
		</li>
                  <li pn="section-2.1-3.2.3.1.2.2"> for each registration of a protocol parameter value, the source
		of the registration and the date of the registration, if the
		date of registration is known, and
		</li>
                  <li pn="section-2.1-3.2.3.1.2.3"> any other information specified as being included in the
		registration data in the RFC document that describes the
		parameter.
		</li>
                  <li pn="section-2.1-3.2.3.1.2.4">
		  If in doubt or in case of a technical dispute, the
		  Registry Operator will seek and follow technical
		  guidance exclusively from the IESG.  Where
		  appropriate, the IESG will appoint an expert to
		  advise the Registry Operator.
		</li>
                </ul>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-2.1-3.2.3.2">
	      The Registry Operator will work with the IETF to develop
	      any missing criteria and procedures over time, which the
	      Registry Operator will adopt when so instructed by the
	      IESG.
	    </li>
              <li pn="section-2.1-3.2.3.3">
	      Unless special circumstances apply to subsets of the
	      data and specific rules are established by IETF
	      consensus, each protocol parameter registry operates as
	      a public registry, and the contents of the registry are
	      openly available to the public, on-line and free of
	      charge.
	    </li>
              <li pn="section-2.1-3.2.3.4">
	      The Registry Operator assigns protocol parameter values in
	      accordance with the policy associated with the protocol
	      parameter, such as "First Come First Served" or "Expert Review"
	      <xref target="RFC8126" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8126"/>.
	    </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-2.1-3.3">
            <t pn="section-2.1-3.3.1">
	  Mailing Lists
	  
            </t>
            <ul spacing="normal" bare="false" empty="false" pn="section-2.1-3.3.2">
              <li pn="section-2.1-3.3.2.1">
	      The Registry Operator maintains public mailing lists as
	      specified in IANA Considerations <xref target="RFC8126" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8126"/>.  Such lists are designated for the
	      purpose of review of assignment proposals in conjunction
	      with a designated expert review function.  In addition,
	      each Registry Operator should
	      maintain a mailing list that enables the registry staff
	      of the Registry Operator to be contacted by email.
	    </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-2.1-3.4">
            <t pn="section-2.1-3.4.1">
	  Liaison Activity
            </t>
            <ul spacing="normal" bare="false" empty="false" pn="section-2.1-3.4.2">
              <li pn="section-2.1-3.4.2.1">
	      The Registry Operator will nominate a liaison point
	      of contact.  The Registry Operator, through this
	      liaison, may be requested to provide advice to the
	      IESG on IETF protocol parameters as well as the
	      "IANA Considerations" section of each Internet-Draft
	      that is being reviewed for publication as an RFC.
	      Where appropriate the IESG will appoint an expert to
	      advise the Registry Operator.
	    </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-2.1-3.5">
            <t pn="section-2.1-3.5.1">
	  Reporting
            </t>
            <ul spacing="normal" bare="false" empty="false" pn="section-2.1-3.5.2">
              <li pn="section-2.1-3.5.2.1">
	      The Registry Operator will submit periodic reports to
	      the IAB concerning the operational performance of the
	      registry function.  As an example of the requirements
	      for such reports, the reader is referred to a supplement
	      <xref target="MoU_SUPP2019" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="MoU_SUPP2019"/> to the "Memorandum of Understanding
	      Concerning the Technical Work of the Internet Assigned
	      Numbers Authority" <xref target="RFC2860" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC2860"/> that provides service level agreement
	      (SLA) guidelines under which ICANN, the current protocol
	      parameter registry, must operate.
	    </li>
              <li pn="section-2.1-3.5.2.2">
	      At the request of the chair of the IETF or IAB, or the
	      IETF Executive Director <xref target="RFC8711" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8711"/>, the Registry Operator will undertake
	      periodic reports to IETF Plenary meetings or elsewhere
	      as directed, concerning the status of the
	      registry function.
	    </li>
              <li pn="section-2.1-3.5.2.3">
	      The Registry Operator will publish an annual report
	      describing the status of the function and a summary of
	      performance indicators.
	    </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-2.1-3.6">
            <t pn="section-2.1-3.6.1"> Intellectual Property Rights and the Registry Operator
            </t>
            <t pn="section-2.1-3.6.2">
         Unless special circumstances apply (see above): 
            </t>
            <ul spacing="normal" bare="false" empty="false" pn="section-2.1-3.6.3">
              <li pn="section-2.1-3.6.3.1">All assigned values are to be published and made
	    available free of any charges.
	    </li>
              <li pn="section-2.1-3.6.3.2">
	      The assignment values may be redistributed without
	      modification.
	      </li>
            </ul>
            <t pn="section-2.1-3.6.4">In any case,</t>
            <ul bare="false" empty="false" spacing="normal" pn="section-2.1-3.6.5">
              <li pn="section-2.1-3.6.5.1">
	      any intellectual property rights of the IETF protocol
	      parameter assignment information, including the IETF
	      protocol parameter registry and its contents, are to be
	      held by the IETF Trust <xref target="RFC8711" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8711"/>
                <xref target="RFC8714" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8714"/>. 
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="include" anchor="IABrole" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-2.2">
        <name slugifiedName="name-iab-role">IAB Role</name>
        <t pn="section-2.2-1">
      An Operator of an IETF protocol parameter registry
	  undertakes the role as a delegated function under the
	  authority of the IAB.
        </t>
        <t pn="section-2.2-2">
	  The IAB has the responsibility to review the current
	  description of the registry function from time to time and
	  direct the Registry Operator to adopt amendments relating to
	  its role and mode of operation according to the best
	  interests of the IETF and the Internet community in general.
        </t>
        <t pn="section-2.2-3">
	  The IAB has the responsibility to appoint an organization to
	  undertake the delegated functions of the 
	  Registry Operator for each IETF protocol parameter.
	  Specifically, the IAB defines the role and requirements for
	  the desired functions.  The IETF LLC is responsible for
	  identifying a potential vendor, and once under agreement,
	  managing the various aspects of the relationships with that
	  vendor.  To be clear, the IAB is in the deciding role (e.g.,
	  for appointment and termination), but must work in close
	  consultation with the IETF LLC.
        </t>
        <t pn="section-2.2-4">
	  The IAB has the responsibility to determine the terms and
	  conditions of this delegated role.  Such terms and
	  conditions should ensure that the registry operates in a
	  manner that is fully conformant to the functions described
	  in this document.  In addition, such terms and conditions
	  must not restrict the rights and interests of the IETF with
	  respect to the registry contents and maintenance.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-2.3">
        <name slugifiedName="name-iesg-role">IESG Role</name>
        <t pn="section-2.3-1">
	  The IESG is responsible for the technical direction
	  regarding entries into IETF protocol parameter registries
	  and maintaining the policies by which such technical
	  directions are given.  Technical direction itself is
	  provided through the adoption of directives within the "IANA
	  Considerations" section of IETF Stream RFCs or through
	  stand-alone "IANA Considerations" RFCs.
        </t>
        <t pn="section-2.3-2">
	  The IESG shall verify that Internet-Drafts that are offered
	  for publication as IETF Stream RFCs <xref target="RFC8729" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8729"/> include "IANA
	  Considerations" sections when needed, and that "IANA
	  Considerations" sections conform to the current published
	  guidelines.
        </t>
        <t pn="section-2.3-3">
	  Since technical assessment is not generally a responsibility
	  of the Registry Operator, as part of providing the technical
	  direction the IESG is responsible for identifying the
	  technical experts that are required to, where appropriate,
	  review registration requests or resolve open technical
	  questions that relate to the registration of parameters.
        </t>
        <t pn="section-2.3-4"> At its discretion, the IESG will organize the liaison
	activities with the Registry Operator's liaison point of
	contact so as to facilitate clear communications and effective
	operation of the registry function.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-2.4">
        <name slugifiedName="name-role-of-the-ietf-trust">Role of the IETF Trust</name>
        <t pn="section-2.4-1">
	  The IETF Trust <xref target="RFC4371" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC4371"/> was formed to act as the
	  administrative custodian of all copyrights and other
	  intellectual property rights relating to the IETF Standards
	  Process, a function that had previously been performed by the
	  Internet Society (ISOC) and the Corporation for National
	  Research Initiatives (CNRI).
        </t>
        <t pn="section-2.4-2">
	  Any intellectual property rights of IETF protocol parameter
	  assignment information, including the registry and its
	  contents, and all registry publications, are to be held by
	  the IETF Trust on behalf of the IETF.
        </t>
        <t pn="section-2.4-3">
	  The IETF Trust may make such regulations as appropriate for
	  the redistribution of assignment values and registry
	  publications.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-2.5">
        <name slugifiedName="name-role-of-the-ietf-administra">Role of the IETF Administration Limited         Liability Company</name>
        <t pn="section-2.5-1">
	  The IETF Administration Limited Liability Company (IETF LLC)
	  <xref target="RFC8711" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8711"/>
	  is responsible for identifying a potential vendor in a
	  manner of its choosing, based on IAB consultation, and for
	  managing the various aspects of the relationships with that
	  vendor.
        </t>
        <t pn="section-2.5-2">
	  In addition, the IETF LLC has the responsibility to ensure
	  long-term access, stability, and uniqueness across all such
	  registries.  This responsibility is of particular
	  significance in the event that a relation with a Protocol
	  Parameter Registry Operator is terminated.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-3">
      <name slugifiedName="name-miscellaneous-consideration">Miscellaneous Considerations</name>
      <t pn="section-3-1">
	While this document has focused on the creation of protocols by
	the IETF, the requirements provided are generically applicable to
	the extended IETF community as well (e.g., Internet Research Task
	Force (IRTF)).
      </t>
      <t pn="section-3-2">
	The IESG is responsible for the technical direction of the
	IETF protocol parameter registries and maintaining the
	policies by which such technical directions are given.  The
	IESG is responsible, as part of the document approval process
	associated with the IETF Stream RFCs <xref target="RFC8729" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8729"/>, for "IANA Considerations"
	verification.  For the other RFC streams, the approval bodies
	are responsible for verifying that the documents include "IANA
	Considerations" sections when needed, and that "IANA
	Considerations" sections conform to the current published
	guidelines.  In the case that IANA considerations in non-IETF
	document streams lead to a dispute, the IAB makes the final
	decision.
      </t>
      <t pn="section-3-3">
	This document talks about "Registry Operator" (singular), and
	while there are stability and economy-of-scale advantages for
	one single Registry Operator, this document does not exclude having
	different Registry Operators for different protocol registries when
	justified by the circumstances.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-4">
      <name slugifiedName="name-security-considerations">Security Considerations</name>
      <t pn="section-4-1">
	This document does not propose any new protocols and does not
	introduce any new security considerations.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-5">
      <name slugifiedName="name-iana-considerations">IANA Considerations</name>
      <t pn="section-5-1"> This document requires no direct IANA actions in terms of
      the creation or operation of a protocol parameter registry.
      However, this document does define the roles and
      responsibilities of various bodies who are responsible for, and
      associated with, the operation of protocol parameter
      registration functions for the IETF.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references pn="section-6">
      <name slugifiedName="name-informative-references">Informative References</name>
      <referencegroup anchor="BCP9" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/bcp9" derivedAnchor="BCP9">
        <reference anchor="RFC2026" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2026" quoteTitle="true">
          <front>
            <title>The Internet Standards Process -- Revision 3</title>
            <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="S. Bradner">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="1996" month="October"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>This memo documents the process used by the Internet community for the standardization of protocols and procedures.  It defines the stages in the standardization process, the requirements for moving a document between stages and the types of documents used during this process. This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="9"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2026"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC2026"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC5657" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5657" quoteTitle="true">
          <front>
            <title>Guidance on Interoperation and Implementation Reports for Advancement to Draft Standard</title>
            <author initials="L." surname="Dusseault" fullname="L. Dusseault">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="R." surname="Sparks" fullname="R. Sparks">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2009" month="September"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>Advancing a protocol to Draft Standard requires documentation of the interoperation and implementation of the protocol.  Historic reports have varied widely in form and level of content and there is little guidance available to new report preparers.  This document updates the existing processes and provides more detail on what is appropriate in an interoperability and implementation report.   This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="9"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5657"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC5657"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC6410" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6410" quoteTitle="true">
          <front>
            <title>Reducing the Standards Track to Two Maturity Levels</title>
            <author initials="R." surname="Housley" fullname="R. Housley">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="D." surname="Crocker" fullname="D. Crocker">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="E." surname="Burger" fullname="E. Burger">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2011" month="October"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>This document updates the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) Standards Process defined in RFC 2026.  Primarily, it reduces the Standards Process from three Standards Track maturity levels to two. This memo documents an Internet Best Current Practice.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="9"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6410"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC6410"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC7100" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7100" quoteTitle="true">
          <front>
            <title>Retirement of the "Internet Official Protocol Standards" Summary Document</title>
            <author initials="P." surname="Resnick" fullname="P. Resnick">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2013" month="December"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>This document updates RFC 2026 to no longer use STD 1 as a summary of "Internet Official Protocol Standards".  It obsoletes RFC 5000 and requests the IESG to move RFC 5000 (and therefore STD 1) to Historic status.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="9"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7100"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7100"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC7127" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7127" quoteTitle="true">
          <front>
            <title>Characterization of Proposed Standards</title>
            <author initials="O." surname="Kolkman" fullname="O. Kolkman">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="S. Bradner">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <author initials="S." surname="Turner" fullname="S. Turner">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2014" month="January"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>RFC 2026 describes the review performed by the Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG) on IETF Proposed Standard RFCs and characterizes the maturity level of those documents.  This document updates RFC 2026 by providing a current and more accurate characterization of Proposed Standards.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="9"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7127"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7127"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC7475" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7475" quoteTitle="true">
          <front>
            <title>Increasing the Number of Area Directors in an IETF Area</title>
            <author initials="S." surname="Dawkins" fullname="S. Dawkins">
              <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
            </author>
            <date year="2015" month="March"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>This document removes a limit on the number of Area Directors who manage an Area in the definition of "IETF Area".  This document updates RFC 2026 (BCP 9) and RFC 2418 (BCP 25).</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="9"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7475"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7475"/>
        </reference>
      </referencegroup>
      <reference anchor="MoU_SUPP2019" target="https://www.ietf.org/media/documents/FINAL_2019-IETF_MoU_Supplemental_Agreement_Signed_31July19.pdf" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="MoU_SUPP2019">
        <front>
          <title>2019 ICANN-IETF MoU Supplemental Agreement</title>
          <author>
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">IETF Administration LLC</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2019" month="July" day="31"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC2860" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2860" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC2860">
        <front>
          <title>Memorandum of Understanding Concerning the Technical Work of the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority</title>
          <author initials="B." surname="Carpenter" fullname="B. Carpenter">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="F." surname="Baker" fullname="F. Baker">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Roberts" fullname="M. Roberts">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <date year="2000" month="June"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>This document places on record the text of the Memorandum of Understanding concerning the technical work of the IANA that was signed on March 1, 2000 between the IETF and ICANN, and ratified by the ICANN Board on March 10, 2000.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2860"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC2860"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC4371" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4371" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC4371">
        <front>
          <title>BCP 101 Update for IPR Trust</title>
          <author initials="B." surname="Carpenter" fullname="B. Carpenter" role="editor">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="L." surname="Lynch" fullname="L. Lynch" role="editor">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <date year="2006" month="January"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>This document updates BCP 101 to take account of the new IETF Intellectual Property Trust.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="101"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4371"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC4371"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC5226" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5226" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC5226">
        <front>
          <title>Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs</title>
          <author initials="T." surname="Narten" fullname="T. Narten">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="H." surname="Alvestrand" fullname="H. Alvestrand">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <date year="2008" month="May"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>Many protocols make use of identifiers consisting of constants and other well-known values.  Even after a protocol has been defined and deployment has begun, new values may need to be assigned (e.g., for a new option type in DHCP, or a new encryption or authentication transform for IPsec).  To ensure that such quantities have consistent values and interpretations across all implementations, their assignment must be administered by a central authority.  For IETF protocols, that role is provided by the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA).</t>
            <t>In order for IANA to manage a given namespace prudently, it needs guidelines describing the conditions under which new values can be assigned or when modifications to existing values can be made.  If IANA is expected to play a role in the management of a namespace, IANA must be given clear and concise instructions describing that role.  This document discusses issues that should be considered in formulating a policy for assigning values to a namespace and provides guidelines for authors on the specific text that must be included in documents that place demands on IANA.</t>
            <t>This document obsoletes RFC 2434.  This document specifies an Internet Best  Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and  suggestions for improvements.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5226"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC5226"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC8126" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8126" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8126">
        <front>
          <title>Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Cotton" fullname="M. Cotton">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="B." surname="Leiba" fullname="B. Leiba">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="T." surname="Narten" fullname="T. Narten">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <date year="2017" month="June"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>Many protocols make use of points of extensibility that use constants to identify various protocol parameters.  To ensure that the values in these fields do not have conflicting uses and to promote interoperability, their allocations are often coordinated by a central record keeper.  For IETF protocols, that role is filled by the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA).</t>
            <t>To make assignments in a given registry prudently, guidance describing the conditions under which new values should be assigned, as well as when and how modifications to existing values can be made, is needed.  This document defines a framework for the documentation of these guidelines by specification authors, in order to assure that the provided guidance for the IANA Considerations is clear and addresses the various issues that are likely in the operation of a registry.</t>
            <t>This is the third edition of this document; it obsoletes RFC 5226.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="26"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8126"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8126"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC8711" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8711" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8711">
        <front>
          <title>Structure of the IETF Administrative Support Activity, Version 2.0</title>
          <author initials="B." surname="Haberman">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Hall">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Livingood">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <date year="2020" month="February"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="101"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8711"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8711"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC8714" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8714" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8714">
        <front>
          <title>Update to the Process for Selection of Trustees for the IETF Trust</title>
          <author initials="J" surname="Arkko" fullname="Jari Arkko">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="T" surname="Hardie" fullname="Ted Hardie">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <date month="February" year="2020"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="101"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8714"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8714"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC8728" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8729" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8728">
        <front>
          <title>RFC Editor Model (Version 2)</title>
          <author initials="O" surname="Kolkman" fullname="Olaf Kolkman" role="editor">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J" surname="Halpern" fullname="Joel Halpern" role="editor">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="R" surname="Hinden" fullname="Robert Hinden" role="editor">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <date month="February" year="2020"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8728"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8728"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC8729" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8729" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8729">
        <front>
          <title>The RFC Series and RFC Editor</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Housley" role="editor">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="L." surname="Daigle" role="editor">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <date month="February" year="2020"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8729"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8729"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <section numbered="false" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-appendix.a">
      <name slugifiedName="name-iab-members-at-the-time-of-">IAB Members at the Time of Approval</name>
      <t pn="section-appendix.a-1">
	Internet Architecture Board Members at the time this document
	was approved for publication were:

      </t>
      <ul empty="true" spacing="compact" bare="false" pn="section-appendix.a-2">
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.1">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-2.1.1"><contact fullname="Jari Arkko"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.2">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-2.2.1"><contact fullname="Alissa Cooper"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.3">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-2.3.1"><contact fullname="Stephen Farrell"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.4">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-2.4.1"><contact fullname="Wes Hardaker"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.5">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-2.5.1"><contact fullname="Ted Hardie"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.6">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-2.6.1"><contact fullname="Christian Huitema"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.7">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-2.7.1"><contact fullname="Zhenbin Li"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.8">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-2.8.1"><contact fullname="Erik Nordmark"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.9">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-2.9.1"><contact fullname="Mark Nottingham"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.10">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-2.10.1"><contact fullname="Melinda Shore"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.11">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-2.11.1"><contact fullname="Jeff Tantsura"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.12">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-2.12.1"><contact fullname="Martin Thomson"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.13">
          <t pn="section-appendix.a-2.13.1"><contact fullname="Brian Trammell"/></t>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section numbered="false" toc="include" anchor="Acknowledgement" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-appendix.b">
      <name slugifiedName="name-acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</name>
      <t pn="section-appendix.b-1">
	This document was originally adapted from "Guidelines for Writing an IANA
	Considerations Section in RFCs" <xref target="RFC5226" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC5226"/>, and has been modified to
	include explicit reference to Intellectual Property Rights and
	the roles of the IAB and IESG in relation to the IETF Protocol
	Parameter Registry function.
      </t>
      <t pn="section-appendix.b-2">
	The document was updated under auspices of the
	IASA2 working group to reflect the reorganization
	of IETF Administrative Support Activity.  
      </t>
      <t pn="section-appendix.b-3">
	The Internet Architecture Board acknowledges the assistance
	provided by reviewers of drafts of this document, including
	<contact fullname="Scott Bradner"/>, <contact fullname="Brian Carpenter"/>,
	  <contact fullname="Leslie Daigle"/>, <contact fullname="Adrian Farrel"/>,
	<contact fullname="Bob Hinden"/>,
	<contact fullname="Alfred Hoenes"/>, <contact fullname="Paul Hoffman"/>,
	  <contact fullname="Benjamin Kaduk"/>, <contact fullname="Alexey      Melnikov"/>, <contact fullname="Thomas Narten"/>,
	and <contact fullname="Ray Pelletier"/>.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="authors-addresses" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-appendix.c">
      <name slugifiedName="name-authors-addresses">Authors' Addresses</name>
      <author initials="D." surname="McPherson" fullname="Danny McPherson" role="editor">
        <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Verisign, Inc.</organization>
        <address>
          <email>dmcpherson@verisign.com</email>
        </address>
      </author>
      <author initials="O." surname="Kolkman" fullname="Olaf Kolkman" role="editor">
        <organization abbrev="ISOC" showOnFrontPage="true">Internet Society</organization>
        <address>
          <email>kolkman@isoc.org</email>
        </address>
      </author>
      <author initials="J." surname="Klensin" fullname="John C Klensin" role="editor">
        <address>
          <email>john-ietf@jck.com</email>
        </address>
      </author>
      <author initials="G." surname="Huston" fullname="Geoff Huston" role="editor">
        <organization showOnFrontPage="true">APNIC</organization>
        <address>
          <email>gih@apnic.net</email>
        </address>
      </author>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
