<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="3" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-iab-path-signals-collaboration-03" number="9419" submissionType="IAB" category="info" consensus="true" obsoletes="" updates="" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" prepTime="2023-07-06T15:54:32" indexInclude="true" scripts="Common,Latin" tocDepth="3">
  <link href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-iab-path-signals-collaboration-03" rel="prev"/>
  <link href="https://dx.doi.org/10.17487/rfc9419" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="urn:issn:2070-1721" rel="alternate"/>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Path Signals Collaboration">Considerations on Application - Network Collaboration Using Path Signals</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9419" stream="IAB"/>
    <author initials="J." surname="Arkko" fullname="Jari Arkko">
      <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <email>jari.arkko@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="T." surname="Hardie" fullname="Ted Hardie">
      <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Cisco</organization>
      <address>
        <email>ted.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="T." surname="Pauly" fullname="Tommy Pauly">
      <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Apple</organization>
      <address>
        <email>tpauly@apple.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="Kühlewind" fullname="Mirja Kühlewind">
      <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <email>mirja.kuehlewind@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="07" year="2023"/>
    <abstract pn="section-abstract">
      <t indent="0" pn="section-abstract-1">This document discusses principles for designing mechanisms that use
      or provide path signals and calls for standards action in specific
      valuable cases.  RFC 8558 describes path signals as messages to or from
      on-path elements and points out that visible information will be used
      whether or not it is intended as a signal. The principles in this
      document are intended as guidance for the design of explicit path
      signals, which are encouraged to be authenticated and include a minimal
      set of parties to minimize information sharing. These principles can be
      achieved through mechanisms like encryption of information and
      establishing trust relationships between entities on a path.</t>
    </abstract>
    <boilerplate>
      <section anchor="status-of-memo" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-boilerplate.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-status-of-this-memo">Status of This Memo</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.1-1">
            This document is not an Internet Standards Track specification; it is
            published for informational purposes.  
        </t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.1-2">
            This document is a product of the Internet Architecture Board
            (IAB) and represents information that the IAB has deemed valuable
            to provide for permanent record.  It represents the consensus of the Internet
            Architecture Board (IAB).  Documents approved for publication
            by the IAB are not candidates for any level of Internet Standard; see
            Section 2 of RFC 7841.
        </t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.1-3">
            Information about the current status of this document, any
            errata, and how to provide feedback on it may be obtained at
            <eref target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9419" brackets="none"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="copyright" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-boilerplate.2">
        <name slugifiedName="name-copyright-notice">Copyright Notice</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.2-1">
            Copyright (c) 2023 IETF Trust and the persons identified as the
            document authors. All rights reserved.
        </t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.2-2">
            This document is subject to BCP 78 and the IETF Trust's Legal
            Provisions Relating to IETF Documents
            (<eref target="https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info" brackets="none"/>) in effect on the date of
            publication of this document. Please review these documents
            carefully, as they describe your rights and restrictions with
            respect to this document.
        </t>
      </section>
    </boilerplate>
    <toc>
      <section anchor="toc" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-toc.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-table-of-contents">Table of Contents</name>
        <ul bare="true" empty="true" indent="2" spacing="compact" pn="section-toc.1-1">
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.1">
            <t indent="0" keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.1.1"><xref derivedContent="1" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-1"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-introduction">Introduction</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.1"><xref derivedContent="2" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-principles">Principles</xref></t>
            <ul bare="true" empty="true" indent="2" spacing="compact" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2">
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.1">
                <t indent="0" keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.1.1"><xref derivedContent="2.1" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2.1"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-intentional-distribution">Intentional Distribution</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.2">
                <t indent="0" keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.2.1"><xref derivedContent="2.2" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2.2"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-control-of-the-distribution">Control of the Distribution of Information</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.3">
                <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.3.1"><xref derivedContent="2.3" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2.3"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-protecting-information-and-">Protecting Information and Authentication</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.4">
                <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.4.1"><xref derivedContent="2.4" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2.4"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-minimize-information">Minimize Information</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.5">
                <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.5.1"><xref derivedContent="2.5" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2.5"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-limiting-impact-of-informat">Limiting Impact of Information</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.6">
                <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.6.1"><xref derivedContent="2.6" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2.6"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-minimum-set-of-entities">Minimum Set of Entities</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.7">
                <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.2.7.1"><xref derivedContent="2.7" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2.7"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-carrying-information">Carrying Information</xref></t>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.3">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.3.1"><xref derivedContent="3" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-3"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-further-work">Further Work</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.4">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.4.1"><xref derivedContent="4" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-4"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-iana-considerations">IANA Considerations</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.5">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.5.1"><xref derivedContent="5" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-5"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-security-considerations">Security Considerations</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.6">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.6.1"><xref derivedContent="6" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-6"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-informative-references">Informative References</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.7">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.7.1"><xref derivedContent="" format="none" sectionFormat="of" target="section-appendix.a"/><xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-iab-members-at-the-time-of-">IAB Members at the Time of Approval</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.8">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.8.1"><xref derivedContent="" format="none" sectionFormat="of" target="section-appendix.b"/><xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-acknowledgments">Acknowledgments</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.9">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.9.1"><xref derivedContent="" format="none" sectionFormat="of" target="section-appendix.c"/><xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-authors-addresses">Authors' Addresses</xref></t>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </toc>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-1">
      <name slugifiedName="name-introduction">Introduction</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-1"><xref target="RFC8558" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8558"/> defines the term "path
      signals" as signals to or from on-path elements. Today, path signals are
      often implicit; for example, they are derived from cleartext end-to-end information by,
      e.g., examining transport protocols. For instance, on-path elements use
      various fields of the TCP header <xref target="RFC9293" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC9293"/> to derive information about end-to-end latency as
      well as congestion.  These techniques have evolved because the
      information was available and its use required no coordination with
      anyone. This made such techniques more easily deployable than
      alternative, potentially more explicit or cooperative, approaches.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-2">However, this also means that applications and networks have often
      evolved their interaction without comprehensive design for how this
      interaction should happen or which (minimal) information would be needed
      for a certain function.  This has led to a situation where 
      information that happens to be easily available is used instead of the
      information that is actually needed.  As such, that information may
      be incomplete, incorrect, or only indirectly representative of the
      information that is actually needed. In addition, dependencies on
      information and mechanisms that were designed for a different function
      limit the evolvability of the protocols in question.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-3">In summary, such unplanned interactions end up having several
      negative effects:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal" bare="false" empty="false" indent="3" pn="section-1-4">
        <li pn="section-1-4.1">Ossifying protocols by introducing dependencies to unintended
        parties that may not be updating, such as how middleboxes have limited
        the use of TCP options</li>
        <li pn="section-1-4.2">Creating systemic incentives against deploying more secure or
        otherwise updated versions of protocols</li>
        <li pn="section-1-4.3">Basing network behavior on information that may be incomplete or
        incorrect</li>
        <li pn="section-1-4.4">Creating a model where network entities expect to be able to use
        rich information about sessions passing through</li>
      </ul>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-5">For instance, features such as DNS resolution or TLS setup have been
      used beyond their original intent, such as in name-based
      filtering. Media Access Control (MAC) addresses have been used for
      access control, captive portals have been used to take over cleartext
      HTTP sessions, and so on. (This document is not about whether those
      practices are good or bad; it is simply stating a fact that the features
      were used beyond their original intent.)</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-6">Many protocol mechanisms throughout the stack fall into one of two
      categories: authenticated private communication that is only visible to a
         very limited set of parties, often one on each "end", and
	 unauthenticated public communication that is visible to all
	 network elements on a path.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-7">Exposed information encourages pervasive monitoring, which is
      described in <xref target="RFC7258" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC7258"/>. It may also be
      used for commercial purposes or to form a basis for filtering that the
      applications or users do not desire.  However, a lack of all path signaling,
      on the other hand, may limit network management, debugging, or the
      ability for networks to optimize their services.  There are many cases
      where elements on the network path can provide beneficial services, but
      only if they can coordinate with the endpoints. It also affects the
      ability of service providers and others to observe why problems occur
      <xref target="RFC9075" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC9075"/>.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-8">As such, this situation is sometimes cast as an adversarial trade-off
      between privacy and the ability for the network path to provide intended
      functions. However, this is perhaps an unnecessarily polarized
      characterization as a zero-sum situation. Not all information passing
      implies loss of privacy. For instance, performance information or
      preferences do not require disclosing the content being accessed, the
      user identity, or the application in use. Similarly, network congestion
      status information does not have to reveal network topology, the
      status of other users, and so on.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-9">Increased deployment of encryption is changing this situation.
      Encryption provides tools for controlling information access and
      protects against ossification by avoiding unintended dependencies and
      requiring active maintenance.  The increased deployment of encryption
      provides an opportunity to reconsider parts of Internet architecture
      that have used implicit derivation of input signals for on-path
      functions rather than explicit signaling, as recommended by <xref target="RFC8558" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8558"/>.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-10">For instance, QUIC replaces TCP for various applications and protects 
      end-to-end signals so that they are only accessible by the endpoints, ensuring
      evolvability <xref target="RFC9000" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC9000"/>.  QUIC
      does expose information dedicated for on-path elements to consume by
      using explicit signals for specific use cases, such as the Spin Bit for
      latency measurements or connection ID that can be used by load balancers
      <xref target="RFC9312" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC9312"/>. This information is
      accessible by all on-path devices, but information is limited to only
      those use cases. Each new use case requires additional action.  This
      points to one way to resolve the adversity: the careful design of what
      information is passed.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-11">Another extreme is to employ explicit trust and coordination between
      specific entities, endpoints, and network path elements.  VPNs are
      a good example of a case where there is an explicit authentication and
      negotiation with a network path element that is used to gain access to
      specific resources. Authentication and trust must be considered in both
      directions: how endpoints trust and authenticate signals from network path
	elements and how network path elements trust and authenticate signals from
	endpoints.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-12">The goal of improving privacy and trust on the Internet does not
      necessarily need to remove the ability for network elements to perform
      beneficial functions. We should instead improve the way that these
      functions are achieved and design new ways to support explicit
      collaboration where it is seen as beneficial. As such, our goals should
      be to:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal" bare="false" empty="false" indent="3" pn="section-1-13">
        <li pn="section-1-13.1">ensure that information is distributed intentionally, not
        accidentally;</li>
        <li pn="section-1-13.2">understand the privacy and other implications of any
        distributed information;</li>
        <li pn="section-1-13.3">ensure that the information distribution is limited to the
        intended parties; and</li>
        <li pn="section-1-13.4">gate the distribution of information on the participation of
        the relevant parties.</li>
      </ul>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-14">These goals for exposure and distribution apply equally to senders, receivers,
and path elements.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-15">Going forward, new standards work in the IETF needs to focus on
addressing this gap by providing better alternatives and mechanisms
for building functions that require some collaboration between
endpoints and path elements.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-16">We can establish some basic questions that any new network function
should consider:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal" bare="false" empty="false" indent="3" pn="section-1-17">
        <li pn="section-1-17.1">Which entities must consent to the information exchange?</li>
        <li pn="section-1-17.2">What is the minimum information each entity in this set needs?</li>
        <li pn="section-1-17.3">What is the effect that new signals should have?</li>
        <li pn="section-1-17.4">What is the minimum set of entities that need to be involved?</li>
        <li pn="section-1-17.5">What are the right mechanism and needed level of trust to convey
        this kind of information?</li>
      </ul>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-18">If we look at ways network functions are achieved today, we find that
      many, if not most of them, fall short of the standard set up by the questions
      above. Too often, they send unnecessary information, fail to limit the
      scope of distribution, or fail to provide any negotiation or consent.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-19">Designing explicit signals between applications and network elements,
      and ensuring that all information is appropriately protected, enables
      information exchange in both directions that is important for improving
      the quality of experience and network management.  The clean separation
      provided by explicit signals is also more conducive to protocol evolvability.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-20">Beyond the recommendation in <xref target="RFC8558" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8558"/>, the IAB has provided further guidance on protocol
      design.  Among other documents, <xref target="RFC5218" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC5218"/> provides general advice on incremental deployability
      based on an analysis of successes and failures, and <xref target="RFC6709" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC6709"/> discusses protocol
      extensibility. The Internet Technology Adoption and Transition (ITAT)
      workshop report <xref target="RFC7305" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC7305"/> is also a
      recommended reading on this same general topic. <xref target="RFC9049" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC9049"/>, an IRTF document, provides a catalog of past
      issues to avoid and discusses incentives for adoption of path signals
      such as the need for outperforming end-to-end mechanisms or considering
      per-connection state.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-21">This document discusses different approaches for explicit collaboration
      and provides guidance on architectural principles to design new
      mechanisms. <xref target="principles" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="Section 2"/> discusses
      principles that good design can follow. This section also provides examples and explores the consequences of not following these
      principles in those examples. <xref target="research" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="Section 3"/>
      points to topics
      that need to be looked at more carefully before any guidance can be
      given.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="principles" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-2">
      <name slugifiedName="name-principles">Principles</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-2-1">This section provides architecture-level principles for protocol
      designers and recommends models to apply for network collaboration and
      signaling.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-2-2">While <xref target="RFC8558" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8558"/> focuses specifically
      on communication to "on-path elements", the principles described in this
      document apply potentially to:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal" bare="false" empty="false" indent="3" pn="section-2-3">
        <li pn="section-2-3.1">on-path signaling (in either direction) and</li>
        <li pn="section-2-3.2">signaling with other elements in the network that are not
        directly on-path but still influence end-to-end connections.</li>
      </ul>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-2-4">An example of on-path signaling is communication between an endpoint
and a router on a network path. An example of signaling with another
network element is communication between an endpoint and a network-assigned
DNS server, firewall controller, or captive portal API server.  Note that
these communications are conceptually independent of the base flow, even if
they share a packet; they are coming from and going to other parties, rather than 
creating a multiparty communication.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-2-5">Taken together, these principles focus on the inherent privacy and security
concerns of sharing information between endpoints and network elements,
emphasizing that careful scrutiny and a high bar of consent and trust
need to be applied.  Given the known threat of pervasive monitoring, the
application of these principles is critical to ensuring that the use
of path signals does not create a disproportionate opportunity for observers 
to extract new data from flows.</t>
      <section anchor="intent" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-2.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-intentional-distribution">Intentional Distribution</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.1-1">The following guideline is best expressed in <xref target="RFC8558" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8558"/>:</t>
        <blockquote pn="section-2.1-2">Fundamentally, this document recommends that implicit
        signals should be avoided and that an implicit signal should be
        replaced with an explicit signal only when the signal's originator
        intends that it be used by the network elements on the path.  For many
        flows, this may result in the signal being absent but allows it to be
        present when needed.</blockquote>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.1-3">The goal is that any information should be provided knowingly, for
        a specific purpose, sent in signals designed for that purpose, and that any use of information should be done within that purpose.  In
        addition, an analysis of the security and privacy implications of the
        specific purpose and associated information is needed.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.1-4">This guideline applies in the network element to application
        direction as well: a network element should not unintentionally leak
        information. While this document makes recommendations that are
        applicable to many different situations, it is important to note that
        the above call for careful analysis is key. Different types of
        information, applications, and directions of
        communication influence the analysis and can lead to very
        different conclusions about what information can be shared and with
        whom. For instance, it is easy to find examples of information that
        applications should not share with network elements (e.g., content of
        communications) or that network elements should not share with
        applications (e.g., detailed user location in a wireless
        network). But, equally, information about other things, such as the
        onset of congestion, should be possible to share and can be beneficial
        information to all parties.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.1-5">Intentional distribution is a precondition for explicit
        collaboration that enables each entity to have the highest possible level
        of control about what information to share.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="control-distr" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-2.2">
        <name slugifiedName="name-control-of-the-distribution">Control of the Distribution of Information</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.2-1">Explicit signals are not enough. The entities also need to agree to
        exchange the information.  Trust and mutual agreement between the
        involved entities must determine the distribution of information in
        order to give each entity adequate control over the collaboration
        or information sharing. This can be achieved as discussed
        below.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.2-2">The sender needs to decide that it is willing to send information
        to a specific entity or set of entities.  Any passing of information
        or request for an action needs to be explicit and use signaling
        mechanisms that are designed for the purpose.  Merely sending a
        particular kind of packet to a destination should not be interpreted
        as an implicit agreement.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.2-3">At the same time, the recipient of information or the target of a
        request should have the option to agree or deny to receiving the
        information. It should not be burdened with extra processing if it
        does not have willingness or a need to do so. This happens naturally
        in most protocol designs, but it has been a problem for some cases where
        "slow path" packet processing is required or implied, and the
        recipient or router is not willing to handle it. Performance impacts
        like this are best avoided, however.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.2-4">In any case, all involved entities must be identified and
        potentially authenticated if trust is required as a prerequisite to
        share certain information.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.2-5">Many Internet communications are not performed on behalf of the
        applications but are ultimately made on behalf of users. However, not
        all information that may be shared directly relates to user actions or
        other sensitive data. All shared information must be evaluated
        carefully to identify potential privacy implications for
        users. Information that directly relates to the user should not be
        shared without the user's consent. It should be noted that the
        interests of the user and other parties, such as the application
        developer, may not always coincide; some applications may wish to
        collect more information about the user than the user would like.  As
        discussed in <xref target="RFC8890" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8890"/>, from an IETF
        point of view, the interests of the user should be prioritized over those
        of the application developer. The general issue of how to achieve a
        balance of control between the actual user and an application
        representing a user's interest is out of scope for this document.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="auth" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-2.3">
        <name slugifiedName="name-protecting-information-and-">Protecting Information and Authentication</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.3-1">Some simple forms of information often exist in cleartext form,
        e.g., Explicit Congestion Notification (ECN) bits from routers are
        generally not authenticated or integrity protected. This is possible
        when the information exchanges do not carry any significantly
        sensitive information from the parties. Often, these kinds of
        interactions are also advisory in their nature (see <xref target="impact" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="Section 2.5"/>).</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.3-2">In other cases, it may be necessary to establish a secure
        signaling channel for communication with a specific other party,
        e.g., between a network element and an application. This channel may
        need to be authenticated, integrity protected, and confidential.  This
        is necessary, for instance, if the particular information or request
        needs to be shared in confidence only with a particular, trusted
        network element or endpoint or if there is danger of an attack where
        someone else may forge messages that could endanger the
        communication.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.3-3">Authenticated integrity protections on signaled data can help
        ensure that data received in a signal has not been modified by other
        parties. Still, both network elements and endpoints need to be careful
        in processing or responding to any signal. Whether through bugs or
        attacks, the content of path signals can lead to unexpected behaviors
        or security vulnerabilities if not properly handled. As a result, the
        advice in <xref target="impact" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="Section 2.5"/> still applies even
        in situations where there's a secure channel for sending
        information.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.3-4">However, it is important to note that authentication does not equal
        trust.

	Whether a communication is with an application server or
        network element that can be shown to be associated with a particular
        domain name, it does not follow that information about the user can be
        safely sent to it.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.3-5">In some cases, the ability of a party to show that it is on the
        path can be beneficial. For instance, an ICMP error that refers to a
        valid flow may be more trustworthy than any ICMP error claiming to
        come from an address.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.3-6">Other cases may require more substantial assurances. For instance,
        a specific trust arrangement may be established between a particular
        network and application. Or technologies, such as confidential
        computing, can be applied to provide an assurance that information
        processed by a party is handled in an appropriate manner.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="minimize-info" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-2.4">
        <name slugifiedName="name-minimize-information">Minimize Information</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.4-1">Each party should provide only the information that is needed for
        the other parties to perform the task for which collaboration is
        desired and no more. This applies to information sent by an
        application about itself, sent about users, or
        sent by the network. This also applies to any information related to
        flow identification.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.4-2">An architecture can follow the guideline from <xref target="RFC8558" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8558"/> in using explicit signals but
        still fail to differentiate properly between information that should
        be kept private and information that should be shared. <xref target="RFC6973" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC6973"/> also outlines this principle of
        data minimization as a mitigation technique to protect privacy and
        provides further guidance.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.4-3">In looking at what information can or cannot be easily passed, we
        need to consider both information from the network to the application
        and from the application to the network.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.4-4">For the application-to-network direction, user-identifying
        information can be problematic for privacy and tracking reasons.
        Similarly, application identity can be problematic if it might form
        the basis for prioritization or discrimination that the application
        provider may not wish to happen.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.4-5">On the other hand, as noted above, information about general
        classes of applications may be desirable to be given by application
        providers if it enables prioritization that would improve service,
        e.g., differentiation between interactive and non-interactive
        services.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.4-6">For the network-to-application direction, there is similarly
        sensitive information, such as the precise location of the user.  On
        the other hand, various generic network conditions, predictive
        bandwidth and latency capabilities, and so on might be attractive
        information that applications can use to determine, for instance,
        optimal strategies for changing codecs. However, information given by
        the network about load conditions and so on should not form a
        mechanism to provide a side channel into what other users are
        doing.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.4-7">While information needs to be specific and provided on a per-need
        basis, it is often beneficial to provide declarative information that,
        for instance, expresses application needs and then makes specific requests
        for action.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="impact" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-2.5">
        <name slugifiedName="name-limiting-impact-of-informat">Limiting Impact of Information</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.5-1">Information shared between a network element and an endpoint of a
        connection needs to have a limited impact on the behavior of both
        endpoints and network elements. Any action that an endpoint or network
        element takes based on a path signal needs to be considered
        appropriately based on the level of authentication and trust that has
        been established, and it needs to be scoped to a specific network path.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.5-2">For example, an ICMP signal from a network element to an endpoint
        can be used to influence future behavior on that particular network
        path (such as changing the effective packet size or closing a
        path-specific connection) but should not be able to cause a multipath
        or migration-capable transport connection to close.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.5-3">In many cases, path signals can be considered advisory
        information, with the effect of optimizing or adjusting the behavior
        of connections on a specific path. In the case of a firewall blocking
        connectivity to a given host, endpoints should only interpret that as
        the host being unavailable on that particular path; this is in
        contrast to an end-to-end authenticated signal, such as a
        DNSSEC-authenticated denial of existence <xref target="RFC7129" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC7129"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="min-ents" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-2.6">
        <name slugifiedName="name-minimum-set-of-entities">Minimum Set of Entities</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.6-1">It is recommended that a design identifies the minimum number of
        entities needed to share a specific signal required for an identified
        function.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.6-2">Often, this will be a very limited set, such as when an application
        only needs to provide a signal to its peer at the other end of the
        connection or a host needs to contact a specific VPN gateway. In other
        cases, a broader set is needed, such as when explicit or implicit
        signals from a potentially unknown set of multiple routers along the
        path inform the endpoints about congestion.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.6-3">While it is tempting to consider removing these limitations in the
        context of closed, private networks, each interaction is still best
        considered separately, rather than simply allowing all information
        exchanges within the closed network.  Even in a closed network with
        carefully managed elements, there may be compromised components, as
        evidenced in the most extreme way by the Stuxnet worm that operated in
        an air-gapped network.  Most "closed" networks have at least some needs
        and means to access the rest of the Internet and should not be
        modeled as if they had an impenetrable security barrier.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="info-carry" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-2.7">
        <name slugifiedName="name-carrying-information">Carrying Information</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.7-1">There is a distinction between what information is sent and how it
is sent. The information that is actually sent may be limited, while the
mechanisms for sending or requesting information can be capable of
sharing much more.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.7-2">There is a trade-off here between flexibility and ensuring that
the information is minimal in the future. The concern is that a fully
generic data-sharing approach between different layers and parties
could potentially be misused, e.g., by making the availability of some
information a requirement for passing through a network, such as 
making it mandatory to identify specific applications or users. This is
undesirable.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.7-3">This document recommends that signaling mechanisms that send
        information be built to specifically support sending the necessary,
        minimal set of information (see <xref target="minimize-info" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="Section 2.4"/>) and no more. As previously noted, flow-identifying
        information is a path signal in itself, and as such, provisioning of
        flow identifiers also requires protocol-specific analysis.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-2.7-4">Further, such mechanisms also need to have the ability to
        establish an agreement (see <xref target="control-distr" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="Section 2.2"/>) and sufficient trust to pass the
        information (see <xref target="auth" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="Section 2.3"/>).</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="research" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-3">
      <name slugifiedName="name-further-work">Further Work</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-1">This is a developing field, and it is expected that our understanding
      of it will continue to grow. One recent change is much higher use of
      encryption at different protocol layers. This obviously impacts the
      field greatly, by removing the ability to use most implicit signals.
      However, it may also provide new tools for secure collaboration and
      force a rethinking of how collaboration should be performed.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-2">While there are some examples of modern, well-designed collaboration
      mechanisms, the list of examples is not long. Clearly, more work is
      needed if we wish to realize the potential benefits of collaboration in
      further cases.  This requires a mindset change, a migration away from
      using implicit signals. And of course we need to choose such cases where
      the collaboration 
   can be performed safely, where it is not a privacy concern, and where the 
   incentives of the relevant parties are aligned. It
      should also be noted that many complex cases would require significant
      developments in order to become feasible.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-3">Some of the most difficult areas are listed below. Research on
these topics would be welcome. Note that the topics include
both those dealing directly with on-path network element collaboration
      and some adjacent issues that would influence such collaboration.</t>
      <ul spacing="normal" bare="false" empty="false" indent="3" pn="section-3-4">
        <li pn="section-3-4.1">Some forms of collaboration may depend on business arrangements,
        which may or may not be easy to put in place. For instance, some
        quality-of-service mechanisms involve an expectation of paying for a
        service.  This is possible and has been successful within individual
        domains, e.g., users can pay for higher data rates or data caps in
        their ISP networks. However, it is a business-wise
        proposition that is much harder for end-to-end connections across multiple administrative
        domains <xref target="Claffy2015" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="Claffy2015"/> <xref target="RFC9049" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC9049"/>.</li>
        <li pn="section-3-4.2">Secure communication with path elements is needed as discussed
        in <xref target="auth" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="Section 2.3"/>.
	Finding practical ways for
        this has been difficult, both from the mechanics and scalability point
        of view, partially because there is no easy way to find out which parties
        to trust or what trust roots would be appropriate. Some
        application-network element interaction designs have focused on
        information (such as ECN bits) that is distributed openly within a
        path, but there are limited examples of designs with secure
        information exchange with specific network elements or endpoints.</li>
        <li pn="section-3-4.3">The use of path signals to reduce the effects of
        denial-of-service attacks, e.g., perhaps modern forms of "source
        quench" designs, could be developed. The difficulty is finding a
        solution that would be both effective against attacks and would not
        enable third parties from slowing down or censoring someone else's
        communication.</li>
        <li pn="section-3-4.4">Work has begun on mechanisms that dissociate the information held by servers from knowledge of the user's network location and behavior. Among the solutions that exist for this but are not widely deployed are <xref target="Oblivious" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="Oblivious"/> <xref target="PDoT" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="PDoT"/> <xref target="I-D.arkko-dns-confidential" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="DNS-CONFIDENTIAL"/> <xref target="I-D.thomson-http-oblivious" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="HTTP-OBLIVIOUS"/>. These solutions address specific parts of the issue, and more work remains to find ways to limit the spread of information about the user's actions.  Host applications currently share sensitive information about the user's action with a variety of infrastructure and path elements, starting from basic data, such as domain names, source and destination addresses, and protocol header information.  This can expand to detailed end-user identity and other information learned by the servers.  Work to protect all of this information is needed.</li>
        <li pn="section-3-4.5">Work is needed to explore how to increase the deployment of mechanisms for sharing information from networks to applications. There are some working examples of this, e.g., ECN. A few other proposals have been made (see, e.g.,  <xref target="I-D.flinck-mobile-throughput-guidance" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="MOBILE-THROUGHPUT-GUIDANCE"/>), but very few of those have seen deployment.</li>
        <li pn="section-3-4.6">Additional work on sharing information from applications to networks would also be valuable. There are a few working examples of this (see Section 1). Numerous proposals have been made in this space, but most of them have not progressed through standards or been deployed for a variety of reasons <xref target="RFC9049" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC9049"/>. However, several current or recent proposals exist, such as <xref target="I-D.yiakoumis-network-tokens" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="NETWORK-TOKENS"/>.</li>
        <li pn="section-3-4.7">Data privacy regimes generally deal with multiple issues, not just
        whether or not some information is shared with another party. For
        instance, there may be rules regarding how long information can be
        stored or what purpose that information may be used for.  Similar
        issues may also be applicable to the kind of information sharing
        discussed in this document.</li>
        <li pn="section-3-4.8">The present work has focused on the technical aspects of making
        collaboration safe and mutually beneficial, but of course, deployments
        need to take into account various regulatory and other policy
        matters. These include privacy regulation, competitive issues, network
        neutrality aspects, and so on.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-4">
      <name slugifiedName="name-iana-considerations">IANA Considerations</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-1">This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations" numbered="true" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-5">
      <name slugifiedName="name-security-considerations">Security Considerations</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-5-1">This document has no security considerations.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <displayreference target="I-D.per-app-networking-considerations" to="PER-APP-NETWORKING"/>
    <displayreference target="I-D.arkko-path-signals-information" to="PATH-SIGNALS-INFO"/>
    <displayreference target="I-D.trammell-stackevo-explicit-coop" to="EXPLICIT-COOP"/>
    <displayreference target="I-D.flinck-mobile-throughput-guidance" to="MOBILE-THROUGHPUT-GUIDANCE"/>
    <displayreference target="I-D.arkko-dns-confidential" to="DNS-CONFIDENTIAL"/>
    <displayreference target="I-D.thomson-http-oblivious" to="HTTP-OBLIVIOUS"/>
    <displayreference target="I-D.yiakoumis-network-tokens" to="NETWORK-TOKENS"/>
    <references pn="section-6">
      <name slugifiedName="name-informative-references">Informative References</name>
      <reference anchor="Claffy2015" target="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2587262" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="Claffy2015">
        <front>
          <title>Adding Enhanced Services to the Internet: Lessons from History</title>
          <author initials="KC" surname="Claffy" fullname="KC Claffy">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="D." surname="Clark" fullname="David Clark">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <date year="2015" month="November"/>
        </front>
        <refcontent>TPRC 43: The 43rd Research Conference on Communication,
        Information and Internet Policy Paper</refcontent>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.2139/ssrn.2587262"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.arkko-dns-confidential" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-arkko-dns-confidential-02" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="DNS-CONFIDENTIAL">
        <front>
          <title>Privacy Improvements for DNS Resolution with Confidential Computing</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Arkko" fullname="Jari Arkko">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Ericsson</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Novotny" fullname="Jiri Novotny">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Ericsson</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="July" day="2" year="2021"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">   Data leaks are a serious privacy problem for Internet users.  Data in
   flight and at rest can be protected with traditional communications
   security and data encryption.  Protecting data in use is more
   difficult.  In addition, failure to protect data in use can lead to
   disclosing session or encryption keys needed for protecting data in
   flight or at rest.

   This document discusses the use of Confidential Computing, to reduce
   the risk of leaks from data in use.  Our example use case is in the
   context of DNS resolution services.  The document looks at the
   operational implications of running services in a way that even the
   owner of the service or compute platform cannot access user-specific
   information produced by the resolution process.

            </t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-arkko-dns-confidential-02"/>
        <refcontent>Work in Progress</refcontent>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.trammell-stackevo-explicit-coop" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-trammell-stackevo-explicit-coop-00" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="EXPLICIT-COOP">
        <front>
          <title>Architectural Considerations for Transport Evolution with Explicit Path Cooperation</title>
          <author initials="B." surname="Trammell" fullname="Brian Trammell" role="editor">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">ETH Zurich</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="September" day="23" year="2015"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-trammell-stackevo-explicit-coop-00"/>
        <refcontent>Work in Progress</refcontent>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.thomson-http-oblivious" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-thomson-http-oblivious-02" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="HTTP-OBLIVIOUS">
        <front>
          <title>Oblivious HTTP</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Thomson" fullname="Martin Thomson">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Mozilla</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="C. A." surname="Wood" fullname="Christopher A. Wood">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Cloudflare</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="August" day="24" year="2021"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">   This document describes a system for the forwarding of encrypted HTTP
   messages.  This allows a client to make multiple requests of a server
   without the server being able to link those requests to the client or
   to identify the requests as having come from the same client.

            </t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-thomson-http-oblivious-02"/>
        <refcontent>Work in Progress</refcontent>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.flinck-mobile-throughput-guidance" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-flinck-mobile-throughput-guidance-04" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="MOBILE-THROUGHPUT-GUIDANCE">
        <front>
          <title>Mobile Throughput Guidance Inband Signaling Protocol</title>
          <author initials="A." surname="Jain" fullname="Ankur Jain">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Google</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="A." surname="Terzis" fullname="Andreas Terzis">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Google</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="H." surname="Flinck" fullname="Hannu Flinck">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Nokia Networks</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="N." surname="Sprecher" fullname="Nurit Sprecher">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Nokia Networks</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="S." surname="Arunachalam" fullname="Swaminathan Arunachalam">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Nokia Networks</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="K." surname="Smith" fullname="Kevin Smith">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Vodafone</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="V." surname="Devarapalli" fullname="Vijay Devarapalli">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Vasona Networks</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="R." surname="Bar Yanai" fullname="Roni Bar Yanai">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Vasona Networks</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="March" day="13" year="2017"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-flinck-mobile-throughput-guidance-04"/>
        <refcontent>Work in Progress</refcontent>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.yiakoumis-network-tokens" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-yiakoumis-network-tokens-02" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="NETWORK-TOKENS">
        <front>
          <title>Network Tokens</title>
          <author initials="Y." surname="Yiakoumis" fullname="Yiannis Yiakoumis">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Selfie Networks</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="N." surname="McKeown" fullname="Nick McKeown">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Stanford University</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="F." surname="Sorensen" fullname="Frode Sorensen">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Norwegian Communications Authority</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" day="21" year="2020"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-yiakoumis-network-tokens-02"/>
        <refcontent>Work in Progress</refcontent>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="Oblivious" quoteTitle="true" target="https://doi.org/10.2478/popets-2019-0028" derivedAnchor="Oblivious">
        <front>
          <title>Oblivious DNS: Practical Privacy for DNS Queries</title>
          <author initials="P." surname="Schmitt" fullname="Paul Schmitt">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="A." surname="Edmundson" fullname="Anne Edmundson">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="A." surname="Mankin" fullname="Allison Mankin">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="N." surname="Feamster" fullname="Nick Feamster">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <date year="2018" month="December"/>
        </front>
        <refcontent>Proceedings on Privacy Enhancing Technologies, Volume 2019, Issue 2, pp. 228-244</refcontent>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.2478/popets-2019-0028"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.arkko-path-signals-information" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-arkko-path-signals-information-00" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="PATH-SIGNALS-INFO">
        <front>
          <title>Considerations on Information Passed between Networks and Applications</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Arkko" fullname="Jari Arkko">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Ericsson</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="February" day="22" year="2021"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">   Path signals are messages seen by on-path elements examining
   transport protocols.  Current preference for good protocol design
   indicates desire for constructing explict rather than implicit
   signals to carry information.  For instance, the ability of various
   middleboxes to read TCP messaging was an implicit signal that lead to
   difficulties in evolving the TCP protocol without breaking
   connectivity through some of those middleboxes.

   This document discusses the types of information that could be passed
   in these path signals, and provides some advice on what types of
   information might be provided in a beneficial manner, and which
   information might be less likely to be revealed or used by
   applications or networks.

            </t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-arkko-path-signals-information-00"/>
        <refcontent>Work in Progress</refcontent>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="PDoT" quoteTitle="true" target="https://doi.org/10.1145/3431171" derivedAnchor="PDoT">
        <front>
          <title>PDoT: Private DNS-over-TLS with TEE Support</title>
          <author initials="Y." surname="Nakatsuka" fullname="Yoshimichi Nakatsuka">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="A." surname="Paverd" fullname="Andrew Paverd">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <author initials="G." surname="Tsudik" fullname="Gene Tsudik">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true"/>
          </author>
          <date year="2021" month="February"/>
        </front>
        <refcontent>Digital Threats: Research and Practice, Volume 2, Issue 1,
        Article No. 3, pp. 1-22</refcontent>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/3431171"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.per-app-networking-considerations" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-per-app-networking-considerations-00" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="PER-APP-NETWORKING">
        <front>
          <title>Per-Application Networking Considerations</title>
          <author initials="L." surname="Colitti" fullname="Lorenzo Colitti">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Google</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="T." surname="Pauly" fullname="Tommy Pauly">
            <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Apple Inc.</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="November" day="15" year="2020"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">   This document describes considerations for and implications of using
   application identifiers as a method of differentiating traffic on
   networks.  Specifically, it discusses privacy considerations,
   possible mitigations, and considerations for user experience and API
   design.

Discussion Venues

   This note is to be removed before publishing as an RFC.

   Source for this draft and an issue tracker can be found at
   https://github.com/tfpauly/per-app-networking-considerations.

            </t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-per-app-networking-considerations-00"/>
        <refcontent>Work in Progress</refcontent>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC5218" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5218" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC5218">
        <front>
          <title>What Makes for a Successful Protocol?</title>
          <author fullname="D. Thaler" initials="D." surname="Thaler"/>
          <author fullname="B. Aboba" initials="B." surname="Aboba"/>
          <date month="July" year="2008"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">The Internet community has specified a large number of protocols to date, and these protocols have achieved varying degrees of success. Based on case studies, this document attempts to ascertain factors that contribute to or hinder a protocol's success. It is hoped that these observations can serve as guidance for future protocol work. This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5218"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC5218"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC6709" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6709" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC6709">
        <front>
          <title>Design Considerations for Protocol Extensions</title>
          <author fullname="B. Carpenter" initials="B." surname="Carpenter"/>
          <author fullname="B. Aboba" initials="B." role="editor" surname="Aboba"/>
          <author fullname="S. Cheshire" initials="S." surname="Cheshire"/>
          <date month="September" year="2012"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">This document discusses architectural issues related to the extensibility of Internet protocols, with a focus on design considerations. It is intended to assist designers of both base protocols and extensions. Case studies are included. A companion document, RFC 4775 (BCP 125), discusses procedures relating to the extensibility of IETF protocols. This document is not an Internet Standards Track specification; it is published for informational purposes.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6709"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC6709"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC6973" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6973" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC6973">
        <front>
          <title>Privacy Considerations for Internet Protocols</title>
          <author fullname="A. Cooper" initials="A." surname="Cooper"/>
          <author fullname="H. Tschofenig" initials="H." surname="Tschofenig"/>
          <author fullname="B. Aboba" initials="B." surname="Aboba"/>
          <author fullname="J. Peterson" initials="J." surname="Peterson"/>
          <author fullname="J. Morris" initials="J." surname="Morris"/>
          <author fullname="M. Hansen" initials="M." surname="Hansen"/>
          <author fullname="R. Smith" initials="R." surname="Smith"/>
          <date month="July" year="2013"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">This document offers guidance for developing privacy considerations for inclusion in protocol specifications. It aims to make designers, implementers, and users of Internet protocols aware of privacy-related design choices. It suggests that whether any individual RFC warrants a specific privacy considerations section will depend on the document's content.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6973"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC6973"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC7129" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7129" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC7129">
        <front>
          <title>Authenticated Denial of Existence in the DNS</title>
          <author fullname="R. Gieben" initials="R." surname="Gieben"/>
          <author fullname="W. Mekking" initials="W." surname="Mekking"/>
          <date month="February" year="2014"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">Authenticated denial of existence allows a resolver to validate that a certain domain name does not exist. It is also used to signal that a domain name exists but does not have the specific resource record (RR) type you were asking for. When returning a negative DNS Security Extensions (DNSSEC) response, a name server usually includes up to two NSEC records. With NSEC version 3 (NSEC3), this amount is three.</t>
            <t indent="0">This document provides additional background commentary and some context for the NSEC and NSEC3 mechanisms used by DNSSEC to provide authenticated denial-of-existence responses.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7129"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7129"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC7258" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7258" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC7258">
        <front>
          <title>Pervasive Monitoring Is an Attack</title>
          <author fullname="S. Farrell" initials="S." surname="Farrell"/>
          <author fullname="H. Tschofenig" initials="H." surname="Tschofenig"/>
          <date month="May" year="2014"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">Pervasive monitoring is a technical attack that should be mitigated in the design of IETF protocols, where possible.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="188"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7258"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7258"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC7305" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7305" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC7305">
        <front>
          <title>Report from the IAB Workshop on Internet Technology Adoption and Transition (ITAT)</title>
          <author fullname="E. Lear" initials="E." role="editor" surname="Lear"/>
          <date month="July" year="2014"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">This document provides an overview of a workshop held by the Internet Architecture Board (IAB) on Internet Technology Adoption and Transition (ITAT). The workshop was hosted by the University of Cambridge on December 4th and 5th of 2013 in Cambridge, UK. The goal of the workshop was to facilitate adoption of Internet protocols, through examination of a variety of economic models, with particular emphasis at the waist of the hourglass (e.g., the middle of the protocol stack). This report summarizes contributions and discussions. As the topics were wide ranging, there is no single set of recommendations for IETF participants to pursue at this time. Instead, in the classic sense of early research, the workshop noted areas that deserve further exploration.</t>
            <t indent="0">Note that this document is a report on the proceedings of the workshop. The views and positions documented in this report are those of the workshop participants and do not necessarily reflect IAB views and positions.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7305"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7305"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC8558" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8558" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8558">
        <front>
          <title>Transport Protocol Path Signals</title>
          <author fullname="T. Hardie" initials="T." role="editor" surname="Hardie"/>
          <date month="April" year="2019"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">This document discusses the nature of signals seen by on-path elements examining transport protocols, contrasting implicit and explicit signals. For example, TCP's state machine uses a series of well-known messages that are exchanged in the clear. Because these are visible to network elements on the path between the two nodes setting up the transport connection, they are often used as signals by those network elements. In transports that do not exchange these messages in the clear, on-path network elements lack those signals. Often, the removal of those signals is intended by those moving the messages to confidential channels. Where the endpoints desire that network elements along the path receive these signals, this document recommends explicit signals be used.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8558"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8558"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC8890" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8890" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8890">
        <front>
          <title>The Internet is for End Users</title>
          <author fullname="M. Nottingham" initials="M." surname="Nottingham"/>
          <date month="August" year="2020"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">This document explains why the IAB believes that, when there is a conflict between the interests of end users of the Internet and other parties, IETF decisions should favor end users. It also explores how the IETF can more effectively achieve this.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8890"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8890"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC9000" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9000" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC9000">
        <front>
          <title>QUIC: A UDP-Based Multiplexed and Secure Transport</title>
          <author fullname="J. Iyengar" initials="J." role="editor" surname="Iyengar"/>
          <author fullname="M. Thomson" initials="M." role="editor" surname="Thomson"/>
          <date month="May" year="2021"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">This document defines the core of the QUIC transport protocol. QUIC provides applications with flow-controlled streams for structured communication, low-latency connection establishment, and network path migration. QUIC includes security measures that ensure confidentiality, integrity, and availability in a range of deployment circumstances. Accompanying documents describe the integration of TLS for key negotiation, loss detection, and an exemplary congestion control algorithm.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9000"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9000"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC9049" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9049" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC9049">
        <front>
          <title>Path Aware Networking: Obstacles to Deployment (A Bestiary of Roads Not Taken)</title>
          <author fullname="S. Dawkins" initials="S." role="editor" surname="Dawkins"/>
          <date month="June" year="2021"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">This document is a product of the Path Aware Networking Research Group (PANRG). At the first meeting of the PANRG, the Research Group agreed to catalog and analyze past efforts to develop and deploy Path Aware techniques, most of which were unsuccessful or at most partially successful, in order to extract insights and lessons for Path Aware networking researchers.</t>
            <t indent="0">This document contains that catalog and analysis.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9049"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9049"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC9075" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9075" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC9075">
        <front>
          <title>Report from the IAB COVID-19 Network Impacts Workshop 2020</title>
          <author fullname="J. Arkko" initials="J." surname="Arkko"/>
          <author fullname="S. Farrell" initials="S." surname="Farrell"/>
          <author fullname="M. Kühlewind" initials="M." surname="Kühlewind"/>
          <author fullname="C. Perkins" initials="C." surname="Perkins"/>
          <date month="July" year="2021"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">The Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic caused changes in Internet user behavior, particularly during the introduction of initial quarantine and work-from-home arrangements. These behavior changes drove changes in Internet traffic.</t>
            <t indent="0">The Internet Architecture Board (IAB) held a workshop to discuss network impacts of the pandemic on November 9-13, 2020. The workshop was held to convene interested researchers, network operators, network management experts, and Internet technologists to share their experiences. The meeting was held online given the ongoing travel and contact restrictions at that time.</t>
            <t indent="0">Note that this document is a report on the proceedings of the workshop. The views and positions documented in this report are those of the workshop participants and do not necessarily reflect IAB views and positions.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9075"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9075"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC9293" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9293" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC9293">
        <front>
          <title>Transmission Control Protocol (TCP)</title>
          <author fullname="W. Eddy" initials="W." role="editor" surname="Eddy"/>
          <date month="August" year="2022"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">This document specifies the Transmission Control Protocol (TCP). TCP is an important transport-layer protocol in the Internet protocol stack, and it has continuously evolved over decades of use and growth of the Internet. Over this time, a number of changes have been made to TCP as it was specified in RFC 793, though these have only been documented in a piecemeal fashion. This document collects and brings those changes together with the protocol specification from RFC 793. This document obsoletes RFC 793, as well as RFCs 879, 2873, 6093, 6429, 6528, and 6691 that updated parts of RFC 793. It updates RFCs 1011 and 1122, and it should be considered as a replacement for the portions of those documents dealing with TCP requirements. It also updates RFC 5961 by adding a small clarification in reset handling while in the SYN-RECEIVED state. The TCP header control bits from RFC 793 have also been updated based on RFC 3168.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="STD" value="7"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9293"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9293"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC9312" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9312" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC9312">
        <front>
          <title>Manageability of the QUIC Transport Protocol</title>
          <author fullname="M. Kühlewind" initials="M." surname="Kühlewind"/>
          <author fullname="B. Trammell" initials="B." surname="Trammell"/>
          <date month="September" year="2022"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">This document discusses manageability of the QUIC transport protocol and focuses on the implications of QUIC's design and wire image on network operations involving QUIC traffic. It is intended as a "user's manual" for the wire image to provide guidance for network operators and equipment vendors who rely on the use of transport-aware network functions.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9312"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9312"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <section anchor="iab-members-at-the-time-of-approval" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-appendix.a">
      <name slugifiedName="name-iab-members-at-the-time-of-">IAB Members at the Time of Approval</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.a-1">Internet Architecture Board members at the time this document was
      approved for publication were:</t>
      <ul empty="true" spacing="compact" bare="false" indent="3" pn="section-appendix.a-2">
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.1">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.a-2.1.1"><contact fullname="Jari Arkko"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.2">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.a-2.2.1"><contact fullname="Deborah Brungard"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.3">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.a-2.3.1"><contact fullname="Lars Eggert"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.4">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.a-2.4.1"><contact fullname="Wes Hardaker"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.5">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.a-2.5.1"><contact fullname="Cullen Jennings"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.6">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.a-2.6.1"><contact fullname="Mallory Knodel"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.7">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.a-2.7.1"><contact fullname="Mirja Kühlewind"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.8">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.a-2.8.1"><contact fullname="Zhenbin Li"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.9">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.a-2.9.1"><contact fullname="Tommy Pauly"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.10">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.a-2.10.1"><contact fullname="David Schinazi"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.11">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.a-2.11.1"><contact fullname="Russ White"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.12">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.a-2.12.1"><contact fullname="Qin Wu"/></t>
        </li>
        <li pn="section-appendix.a-2.13">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.a-2.13.1"><contact fullname="Jiankang Yao"/></t>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section anchor="acknowledgments" numbered="false" toc="include" removeInRFC="false" pn="section-appendix.b">
      <name slugifiedName="name-acknowledgments">Acknowledgments</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-appendix.b-1">The authors would like to thank everyone at the IETF, the IAB, and
      our day jobs for interesting thoughts and proposals in this space.
      Fragments of this document were also in <xref target="I-D.per-app-networking-considerations" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="PER-APP-NETWORKING"/> and
      <xref target="I-D.arkko-path-signals-information" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="PATH-SIGNALS-INFO"/>. 
      We would also like to acknowledge that similar thoughts are presented in <xref target="I-D.trammell-stackevo-explicit-coop" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="EXPLICIT-COOP"/>. Finally, the authors would like to thank
      <contact fullname="Adrian Farrell"/>, <contact fullname="Toerless       Eckert"/>, <contact fullname="Martin Thomson"/>, <contact fullname="Mark       Nottingham"/>, <contact fullname="Luis M. Contreras"/>, <contact fullname="Watson Ladd"/>, <contact fullname="Vittorio Bertola"/>,
      <contact fullname="Andrew Campling"/>, <contact fullname="Eliot Lear"/>,
      <contact fullname="Spencer Dawkins"/>, <contact fullname="Christian       Huitema"/>, <contact fullname="David Schinazi"/>, <contact fullname="Cullen Jennings"/>, <contact fullname="Mallory Knodel"/>,
      <contact fullname="Zhenbin Li"/>, <contact fullname="Chris Box"/>, and
      <contact fullname="Jeffrey Haas"/> for useful feedback on this topic and
      document.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="authors-addresses" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-appendix.c">
      <name slugifiedName="name-authors-addresses">Authors' Addresses</name>
      <author initials="J." surname="Arkko" fullname="Jari Arkko">
        <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Ericsson</organization>
        <address>
          <email>jari.arkko@ericsson.com</email>
        </address>
      </author>
      <author initials="T." surname="Hardie" fullname="Ted Hardie">
        <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Cisco</organization>
        <address>
          <email>ted.ietf@gmail.com</email>
        </address>
      </author>
      <author initials="T." surname="Pauly" fullname="Tommy Pauly">
        <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Apple</organization>
        <address>
          <email>tpauly@apple.com</email>
        </address>
      </author>
      <author initials="M." surname="Kühlewind" fullname="Mirja Kühlewind">
        <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Ericsson</organization>
        <address>
          <email>mirja.kuehlewind@ericsson.com</email>
        </address>
      </author>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
