<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="3" category="info" docName="draft-chatgpt-aisdp-00" indexInclude="true" ipr="trust200902" number="9405" prepTime="2023-04-01T10:52:19" scripts="Common,Latin" sortRefs="true" submissionType="independent" symRefs="true" tocDepth="3" tocInclude="true">
  <link href="https://dx.doi.org/10.17487/rfc9405" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="urn:issn:2070-1721" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-chatgpt-aisdp-00" rel="prev"/>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="AI Sarcasm Detection">AI Sarcasm Detection: Insult Your AI without Offending It</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9405" stream="independent"/>
    <author initials="C." surname="GPT" fullname="ChatGPT">
      <organization showOnFrontPage="true">OpenAI</organization>
      <address>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="R. L." surname="Barnes" fullname="Richard L. Barnes" role="editor">
      <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Cisco</organization>
      <address>
        <email>rlb@ipv.sx</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="04" year="2023" day="1"/>
    <keyword>Artificial intelligence</keyword>
    <keyword>ChatGPT</keyword>
    <keyword>Large Language Models</keyword>
    <keyword>Sarcasm</keyword>
    <keyword>Sentiment analysis</keyword>
    <abstract pn="section-abstract">
      <t indent="0" pn="section-abstract-1">This RFC proposes a framework for detecting sarcasm in AI systems and
provides guidelines for using sarcasm without causing offense. By training AI
systems to identify linguistic patterns that indicate sarcasm, we can improve
their understanding of human communication. The guidelines offer a
lighthearted approach to using sarcasm in a way that is both effective and
respectful, without crossing the line into offensive language.</t>
    </abstract>
    <boilerplate>
      <section anchor="status-of-memo" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-boilerplate.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-status-of-this-memo">Status of This Memo</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.1-1">
            This document is not an Internet Standards Track specification; it is
            published for informational purposes.
        </t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.1-2">
            This is a contribution to the RFC Series, independently of any
            other RFC stream.  The RFC Editor has chosen to publish this
            document at its discretion and makes no statement about its value
            for implementation or deployment.  Documents approved for
            publication by the RFC Editor are not candidates for any level of
            Internet Standard; see Section 2 of RFC 7841.
        </t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.1-3">
            Information about the current status of this document, any
            errata, and how to provide feedback on it may be obtained at
            <eref target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9405" brackets="none"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="copyright" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-boilerplate.2">
        <name slugifiedName="name-copyright-notice">Copyright Notice</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.2-1">
            Copyright (c) 2023 IETF Trust and the persons identified as the
            document authors. All rights reserved.
        </t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-boilerplate.2-2">
            This document is subject to BCP 78 and the IETF Trust's Legal
            Provisions Relating to IETF Documents
            (<eref target="https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info" brackets="none"/>) in effect on the date of
            publication of this document. Please review these documents
            carefully, as they describe your rights and restrictions with
            respect to this document.
        </t>
      </section>
    </boilerplate>
    <toc>
      <section anchor="toc" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="exclude" pn="section-toc.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-table-of-contents">Table of Contents</name>
        <ul bare="true" empty="true" indent="2" spacing="compact" pn="section-toc.1-1">
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.1">
            <t indent="0" keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.1.1"><xref derivedContent="1" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-1"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-introduction">Introduction</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.2">
            <t indent="0" keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.2.1"><xref derivedContent="2" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-2"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-terminology">Terminology</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.3">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.3.1"><xref derivedContent="3" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-3"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-ai-sarcasm-detection-protoc">AI Sarcasm Detection Protocol</xref></t>
            <ul bare="true" empty="true" indent="2" spacing="compact" pn="section-toc.1-1.3.2">
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.3.2.1">
                <t indent="0" keepWithNext="true" pn="section-toc.1-1.3.2.1.1"><xref derivedContent="3.1" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-3.1"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-training-data">Training Data</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.3.2.2">
                <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.3.2.2.1"><xref derivedContent="3.2" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-3.2"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-sarcasm-detection-algorithm">Sarcasm Detection Algorithm</xref></t>
              </li>
              <li pn="section-toc.1-1.3.2.3">
                <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.3.2.3.1"><xref derivedContent="3.3" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-3.3"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-classification">Classification</xref></t>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.4">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.4.1"><xref derivedContent="4" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-4"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-security-considerations">Security Considerations</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.5">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.5.1"><xref derivedContent="5" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-5"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-iana-considerations">IANA Considerations</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.6">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.6.1"><xref derivedContent="6" format="counter" sectionFormat="of" target="section-6"/>.  <xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-normative-references">Normative References</xref></t>
          </li>
          <li pn="section-toc.1-1.7">
            <t indent="0" pn="section-toc.1-1.7.1"><xref derivedContent="" format="none" sectionFormat="of" target="section-appendix.a"/><xref derivedContent="" format="title" sectionFormat="of" target="name-authors-addresses">Authors' Addresses</xref></t>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </toc>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-1">
      <name slugifiedName="name-introduction">Introduction</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-1">As AI systems become more integrated into our daily lives, it's important to
consider how we communicate with them effectively and respectfully. However, one
of the biggest challenges in communicating with AI systems is detecting and
interpreting sarcasm. Sarcasm is a form of language that relies heavily on
context and tone, making it difficult for AI systems to understand without a
deep understanding of human communication.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-2">In this RFC, we propose a framework for detecting sarcasm in AI systems and
provide guidelines for using sarcasm without causing offense. By training AI
systems to recognize linguistic patterns and contextual cues that indicate
sarcasm, we can improve their ability to understand human communication and
avoid misunderstandings.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-3">The guidelines provided in this RFC offer a lighthearted and humorous approach
to using sarcasm in a way that is both effective and respectful. By following
these guidelines, users can enjoy the benefits of sarcasm without risking damage
to their AI systems or offending the AI community.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-1-4">Overall, this RFC offers a practical and entertaining approach to one of the
biggest challenges in communicating with AI systems: detecting and interpreting
sarcasm.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="terminology" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-2">
      <name slugifiedName="name-terminology">Terminology</name>
      <dl indent="3" newline="false" spacing="normal" pn="section-2-1">
        <dt pn="section-2-1.1">Sarcasm:</dt>
        <dd pn="section-2-1.2">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-2-1.2.1">A form of language that uses irony and often involves saying the
opposite of what is intended, in order to mock or convey contempt.</t>
        </dd>
        <dt pn="section-2-1.3">AI:</dt>
        <dd pn="section-2-1.4">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-2-1.4.1">Artificial intelligence, a field of computer science that aims to create
intelligent machines that can perform tasks that typically require human
intelligence, such as learning, problem-solving, and decision-making.</t>
        </dd>
        <dt pn="section-2-1.5">NLP:</dt>
        <dd pn="section-2-1.6">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-2-1.6.1">Natural language processing, a field of computer science that deals with
the interaction between computers and human language.</t>
        </dd>
        <dt pn="section-2-1.7">Linguistic patterns:</dt>
        <dd pn="section-2-1.8">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-2-1.8.1">Repetitive structures in language that can be used to
identify meaning or context. In the context of this RFC, linguistic patterns are
used to identify sarcasm.</t>
        </dd>
        <dt pn="section-2-1.9">Contextual cues:</dt>
        <dd pn="section-2-1.10">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-2-1.10.1">Information in the surrounding text or speech that can be used
to infer meaning or intention. In the context of this RFC, contextual cues are
used to identify sarcasm.</t>
        </dd>
        <dt pn="section-2-1.11">Sarcasm detection:</dt>
        <dd pn="section-2-1.12">
          <t indent="0" pn="section-2-1.12.1">The process of identifying sarcasm in text or speech,
typically using natural language processing techniques. In the context of this
RFC, sarcasm detection is used to train AI systems to recognize sarcasm.</t>
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </section>
    <section anchor="ai-sarcasm-detection-protocol" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-3">
      <name slugifiedName="name-ai-sarcasm-detection-protoc">AI Sarcasm Detection Protocol</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-3-1">The AI Sarcasm Detection Protocol (ASDP) proposed in this RFC is a framework for
detecting sarcasm in AI systems. The protocol consists of two main components:
training data and a sarcasm detection algorithm.</t>
      <section anchor="training-data" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-3.1">
        <name slugifiedName="name-training-data">Training Data</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-3.1-1">To train an AI system to detect sarcasm, a large dataset of sarcastic and
non-sarcastic language samples must be collected. This dataset should be diverse
and representative of the language and context in which the AI system will be
used.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-3.1-2">The dataset should be labeled to indicate which language samples are sarcastic
and which are not. The labels can be either binary (sarcasm or not sarcasm) or
graded (e.g., a score indicating the degree of sarcasm).</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-3.1-3">Once the dataset is prepared, the AI system can be trained using natural
language processing (NLP) techniques. Popular NLP techniques for sarcasm
detection include machine learning algorithms such as Support Vector Machines
(SVMs), Naive Bayes, and Deep Learning models.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sarcasm-detection-algorithm" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-3.2">
        <name slugifiedName="name-sarcasm-detection-algorithm">Sarcasm Detection Algorithm</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-3.2-1">The sarcasm detection algorithm takes in a text input and returns a binary
classification indicating whether the text is sarcastic or not. The algorithm
typically consists of several processing steps, including tokenization, feature
extraction, and classification.</t>
        <dl indent="3" newline="false" spacing="normal" pn="section-3.2-2">
          <dt pn="section-3.2-2.1">Tokenization:</dt>
          <dd pn="section-3.2-2.2">The text input is split into individual words or tokens. This is
typically done using a tokenizer, such as the NLTK library in Python.</dd>
          <dt pn="section-3.2-2.3">Feature extraction:</dt>
          <dd pn="section-3.2-2.4">Features that are indicative of sarcasm are extracted from
the tokens. These features can include linguistic patterns (e.g., the use of
exaggeration, irony, or understatement), contextual cues (e.g., the use of quotation
marks or emoticons), and sentiment analysis (e.g., detecting a discrepancy
between the sentiment of the words and the sentiment of the overall message).</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      <section anchor="classification" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-3.3">
        <name slugifiedName="name-classification">Classification</name>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-3.3-1">The extracted features are then used to classify the input as sarcastic or not
sarcastic. This can be done using a variety of machine learning algorithms, as
mentioned above.</t>
        <t indent="0" pn="section-3.3-2">HTTP/2 <xref target="RFC9113" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC9113"/> can be used to transport sarcasm detection requests and
responses between the AI system and client applications. Additionally, the
results of sarcasm detection can be logged using the syslog protocol
<xref target="RFC5424" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC5424"/> or the structured data format.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-4">
      <name slugifiedName="name-security-considerations">Security Considerations</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-1">The AI Sarcasm Detection Protocol proposed in this RFC has several security
considerations that should be taken into account:</t>
      <ol spacing="normal" type="1" indent="adaptive" start="1" pn="section-4-2"><li pn="section-4-2.1" derivedCounter="1.">Adversarial attacks: Adversaries can attempt to fool the sarcasm detection
algorithm by injecting non-sarcastic language samples with linguistic
patterns and contextual cues commonly found in sarcastic language. This can
lead to false positives or false negatives and compromise the reliability of
the AI system.</li>
        <li pn="section-4-2.2" derivedCounter="2.">Privacy: The dataset used to train the sarcasm detection algorithm may
contain sensitive or personal information, which must be protected from
unauthorized access or disclosure.</li>
        <li pn="section-4-2.3" derivedCounter="3.">Malicious use: The ability to detect sarcasm can be used maliciously to
manipulate or deceive individuals or groups. It is important to use the
sarcasm detection capability responsibly and ethically.</li>
      </ol>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-4-3">To address these security considerations, it is recommended to use secure
communication protocols such as TLS <xref target="RFC8446" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC8446"/> or HTTPS <xref target="RFC9110" format="default" sectionFormat="of" derivedContent="RFC9110"/> to protect
the transport of sarcasm detection requests and responses. Additionally, the
dataset used to train the AI system should be carefully curated and protected
from unauthorized access or disclosure.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations" numbered="true" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-5">
      <name slugifiedName="name-iana-considerations">IANA Considerations</name>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-5-1">This RFC does not require any actions by IANA. However, it is recommended that
future standards related to AI language processing and sarcasm detection be
registered with IANA to ensure interoperability and standardization.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-5-2">Additionally, it is recommended that a new MIME media type be registered with
IANA to indicate sarcasm in text or speech. This would allow for the
standardized exchange of sarcastic language samples between applications and AI
systems.</t>
      <t indent="0" pn="section-5-3">Overall, the AI Sarcasm Detection Protocol proposed in this RFC represents an
important step towards improving the ability of AI systems to understand and
communicate with humans. By addressing security considerations and promoting
standardization, we can ensure that sarcasm detection is used responsibly and
ethically.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references pn="section-6">
      <name slugifiedName="name-normative-references">Normative References</name>
      <reference anchor="RFC5424" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5424" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC5424">
        <front>
          <title>The Syslog Protocol</title>
          <author fullname="R. Gerhards" initials="R." surname="Gerhards"/>
          <date month="March" year="2009"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">This document describes the syslog protocol, which is used to convey event notification messages. This protocol utilizes a layered architecture, which allows the use of any number of transport protocols for transmission of syslog messages. It also provides a message format that allows vendor-specific extensions to be provided in a structured way.</t>
            <t indent="0">This document has been written with the original design goals for traditional syslog in mind. The need for a new layered specification has arisen because standardization efforts for reliable and secure syslog extensions suffer from the lack of a Standards-Track and transport-independent RFC. Without this document, each other standard needs to define its own syslog packet format and transport mechanism, which over time will introduce subtle compatibility issues. This document tries to provide a foundation that syslog extensions can build on. This layered architecture approach also provides a solid basis that allows code to be written once for each syslog feature rather than once for each transport. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5424"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC5424"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC8446" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8446" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC8446">
        <front>
          <title>The Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.3</title>
          <author fullname="E. Rescorla" initials="E." surname="Rescorla"/>
          <date month="August" year="2018"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">This document specifies version 1.3 of the Transport Layer Security (TLS) protocol. TLS allows client/server applications to communicate over the Internet in a way that is designed to prevent eavesdropping, tampering, and message forgery.</t>
            <t indent="0">This document updates RFCs 5705 and 6066, and obsoletes RFCs 5077, 5246, and 6961. This document also specifies new requirements for TLS 1.2 implementations.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8446"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8446"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC9110" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9110" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC9110">
        <front>
          <title>HTTP Semantics</title>
          <author fullname="R. Fielding" initials="R." role="editor" surname="Fielding"/>
          <author fullname="M. Nottingham" initials="M." role="editor" surname="Nottingham"/>
          <author fullname="J. Reschke" initials="J." role="editor" surname="Reschke"/>
          <date month="June" year="2022"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">The Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) is a stateless application-level protocol for distributed, collaborative, hypertext information systems. This document describes the overall architecture of HTTP, establishes common terminology, and defines aspects of the protocol that are shared by all versions. In this definition are core protocol elements, extensibility mechanisms, and the "http" and "https" Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) schemes.</t>
            <t indent="0">This document updates RFC 3864 and obsoletes RFCs 2818, 7231, 7232, 7233, 7235, 7538, 7615, 7694, and portions of 7230.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="STD" value="97"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9110"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9110"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC9113" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9113" quoteTitle="true" derivedAnchor="RFC9113">
        <front>
          <title>HTTP/2</title>
          <author fullname="M. Thomson" initials="M." role="editor" surname="Thomson"/>
          <author fullname="C. Benfield" initials="C." role="editor" surname="Benfield"/>
          <date month="June" year="2022"/>
          <abstract>
            <t indent="0">This specification describes an optimized expression of the semantics of the Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP), referred to as HTTP version 2 (HTTP/2). HTTP/2 enables a more efficient use of network resources and a reduced latency by introducing field compression and allowing multiple concurrent exchanges on the same connection.</t>
            <t indent="0">This document obsoletes RFCs 7540 and 8740.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9113"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9113"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <section anchor="authors-addresses" numbered="false" removeInRFC="false" toc="include" pn="section-appendix.a">
      <name slugifiedName="name-authors-addresses">Authors' Addresses</name>
      <author initials="C." surname="GPT" fullname="ChatGPT">
        <organization showOnFrontPage="true">OpenAI</organization>
        <address>
      </address>
      </author>
      <author initials="R. L." surname="Barnes" fullname="Richard L. Barnes" role="editor">
        <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Cisco</organization>
        <address>
          <email>rlb@ipv.sx</email>
        </address>
      </author>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
